<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>User Group on code.openark.org</title>
    <link>/blog/tags/user-group/</link>
    <description>Recent content in User Group on code.openark.org</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2011 19:16:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/blog/tags/user-group/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL User Group Meeting, June 2011, Israel</title>
      <link>/blog/2011/06/18/mysql-user-group-meeting-june-2011-israel/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2011 19:16:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2011/06/18/mysql-user-group-meeting-june-2011-israel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been quite a while since a MySQL User Group Meeting was held in Israel. I&#39;m happy to announce that the next meeting will take place on &lt;strong&gt;June 28th&lt;/strong&gt;, starting &lt;strong&gt;16:30&lt;/strong&gt;. Talks will be in Hebrew. Full details &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.valinor.co.il/?page_id=1325&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This meeting is organized by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.valinor.co.il/&#34;&gt;Valinor&lt;/a&gt;, who will also be hosting it, and who are planning to make this a tradition. Thumbs up!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rotem Fogel will be presenting on &lt;strong&gt;Reaching best Scalability on MySQL Based Applications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gabi Davis will be presenting on &lt;strong&gt;Working with MySQL in Real Life: Do&#39;s and Don&#39;ts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will be presenting on &lt;strong&gt;MySQL Replication Solutions and Enhancements&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meeting is open to everyone, do come!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL User Group Meetings in Israel</title>
      <link>/blog/2009/03/11/mysql-user-group-meetings-in-israel/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2009 07:42:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2009/03/11/mysql-user-group-meetings-in-israel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a short note that the MySQL User Group Meetings in Israel are established (well, re-established after a very long period).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Eddy Resnick from Sun Microsystems Israel who has set up the meetings. So far, we&#39;ve had 2 successful meetings, and we intend to have more! First one was in Sun&#39;s offices in Herzlia; second one, held last week, was at &lt;a title=&#34;Interbit&#34; href=&#34;http://interbit.co.il/&#34;&gt;Interbit&lt;/a&gt; (a MySQL training center) in Ramat Gan. We hope to hold these meetings on a monthly basis, and the next ones are expected to be held at Interbit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new (blessed) law in Israel forbids us from sending invitations for these meetings via email without prior consent of the recepient (this law has passed as means of stopping spam). We do realize there are many users out there who would be interested in these meeting. For those users: please stay tuned to Interbit&#39;s website, where future meetings will be published - or just give them a call!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was my honor to present a short session, one of three in this last meeting. Other presenters were Erad Deutch, who presented &#34;MySQL Success Stories&#34;, and Moshe Kaplan, who presented &#34;Sharding Solutions&#34;. I have presented &#34;MyISAM &amp;amp; InnoDB Tuning Fundamentals&#34;, where I have layed down the basics behind parameter tuning for these storage engines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per audience request, here&#39;s the &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/03/innodb_myisam_tuning_fundamentals_share.pdf&#34;&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt; in PDF format:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intend to give sessions in future meetings, and have already started working on my next one. So please come, it&#39;s a fun way to pass a nice afternoon. See you there!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>