<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conf on code.openark.org</title>
    <link>/blog/tags/conf/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conf on code.openark.org</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2011 19:53:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/blog/tags/conf/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Impressions from Percona Live, London</title>
      <link>/blog/2011/10/27/impressions-from-percona-live-london/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2011 19:53:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2011/10/27/impressions-from-percona-live-london/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Am now back from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/london-2011/&#34;&gt;Percona Live&lt;/a&gt;, London. Here are some quick impressions of mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The physical location of the conference was excellent, not far from Tower Bridge. The conference area itself was nice and has good atmosphere. Very well organized. Kudos to &lt;em&gt;Percona&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Theme&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official theme for the conference was &lt;em&gt;&#34;Discover the Power of MySQL&#34;&lt;/em&gt;. However, looking back at the conference, I think the de-facto theme was &lt;em&gt;&#34;High Availability and Scale Out for MySQL&#34;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do I say that? Look at the sponsors of the event; look at the talks. There were talks by and about Clustrix, Tungsten (parallel replication), Schooner, Choosing a HA solution (by Henrik), Fusion-IO, MySQL Cluster, MySQL in the Cloud, Galera Replication, Scalebase, Spider, MHA, Various HA Solutions (by Oli Sennhauser)...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were other talks, about all sorts of things. But to me it seemed like scale-out was the big thing, and HA the next one. Especially looking at sponsors booths it looked that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;People&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, it&#39;s no secret that meeting the people is a great fun. I met with familiar faces, and was happy to meet new ones. It&#39;s great to just discuss stuff with people, share opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The after party was fun, and well organized. Kudos to &lt;em&gt;Clustrix&lt;/em&gt; who sponsored it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Business talk&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn&#39;t at the conference to sell anything myself, and so was on a relaxed mood. I was happy that whatever sales talk I shared, heard or overheard was highly technical and very open. It was also good to openly discuss possible relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was in particular pleased to see the popularity some of my tools and ideas were gaining. I could recognize at least two talks where my tools were mentioned; I was delighted to talk to DBAs telling me they were using &lt;em&gt;openark-kit&lt;/em&gt; in general, &lt;a href=&#34;http://openarkkit.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/openarkkit/doc/html/oak-online-alter-table.html&#34;&gt;oak-online-alter-table&lt;/a&gt; in particular, or some SQL solutions and tricks I offered in my blog. This is really wonderful! To write something having people use it to their benefit -- I suppose this is what open source aspires to. It&#39;s great to hear feedback, and better yet to get good feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also had the pleasure of meeting people after hours, and have good discussions, not necessarily MySQL related.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To top it all, I had free time on Wednesday, where I had a superior visit to the Natural History Museum, which left me in awe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>