<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Community on code.openark.org</title>
    <link>/blog/tags/community/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Community on code.openark.org</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2016 17:09:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/blog/tags/community/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Community Awards 2016: Call for Nominations!</title>
      <link>/blog/2016/02/05/mysql-community-awards-2016-call-for-nominations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2016 17:09:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2016/02/05/mysql-community-awards-2016-call-for-nominations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;2016&lt;/strong&gt; MySQL Community Awards event will take place, as usual, in Santa Clara, during the Percona Live Data Performance Conference, April 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MySQL Community Awards is a community based initiative. The idea is to publicly recognize contributors to the MySQL ecosystem. The entire process of discussing, voting and awarding is controlled by an independent group of community members, typically based of past winners or their representatives, as well as known contributors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a self-appointed, self-declared, self-making-up-the-rules-as-it-goes committee. It is also very aware of the importance of the community; a no-nonsense, non-political, adhering to tradition, self criticizing committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Call for Nominations is open. We are seeking the community’s assistance in nominating candidates in the following categories:&lt;span id=&#34;more-7199&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Community Contributor of the year 2016&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a personal award; a winner would a person who has made contribution to the MySQL ecosystem. This could be via development, advocating, blogging, speaking, supporting, etc. All things go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Application of the year 2016&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An application, project, product etc. which supports the MySQL ecosystem by either contributing code, complementing its behaviour, supporting its use, etc. This could range from a one man open source project to a large scale social service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Corporate Contributor of the year 2016&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A company who made contribution to the MySQL ecosystem. This might be a corporate which released major open source code; one that advocates for MySQL; one that help out community members by... anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a list of previous winners, please see &lt;a href=&#34;http://mysqlawards.org/mysql-hall-of-fame/&#34;&gt;MySQL Hall of Fame&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Process of nomination and voting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone can nominate anyone. When nominating, please make sure to provide a brief explanation on why the candidate is eligible to get the award. Make a good case!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee will review all nominations and vote; it typically takes two rounds of votes to pick the winners, and a lot of discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be &lt;em&gt;up to&lt;/em&gt; three winners in each category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods of nomination:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send en email to &lt;strong&gt;mysql.community.awards [ at ] &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;gmail.com&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comment to this post&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assuming you can provide a reasonable description in &lt;strong&gt;140&lt;/strong&gt; characters, tweet your nomination at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=MySQLAwards&amp;amp;src=typd&amp;amp;f=realtime&#34;&gt;#MySQLAwards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please submit your nominations no later than &lt;strong&gt;Monday, February 29, 2016&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The committee&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Members of the committee are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baron Schwartz, Colin Charles, Daniël van Eeden, Davi Arnaut, Frederic Descamps, Geoffrey Anderson, Giuseppe Maxia, Justin Swanhart, Mark Leith, Morgan Tocker, Philip Stoev, Ronald Bradford, Santiago Lertora&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Cole and myself (Shlomi Noach) are acting as co-secretaries; we will be non-voting (except for breaking ties).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee communicates throughout the nomination and voting process to exchange views and opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The awards&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awards are traditionally donated by some party whose identity remains secret. We are now securing the donation, but if you feel an urgent need to be an anonymous donator, please contact us in private, and thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Support&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a community effort; we ask for your support in spreading the word and of course in nominating candidates. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;sharedaddy sd-sharing-enabled&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live Amsterdam: Community Dinner, last updates</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/09/18/percona-live-amsterdam-community-dinner-last-updates/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2015 14:14:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/09/18/percona-live-amsterdam-community-dinner-last-updates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Registration for the Percona Live Amsterdam conference &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/community-dinner-bookingcom-tickets-17901675393&#34;&gt;community dinner at Booking.com&lt;/a&gt; is ongoing. Please note the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By Monday noon the kitchen will make the necessary purchasing. At this time we will have to give them a number, which we will not exceed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number we will give them is &lt;strong&gt;$(number of registrants Monday 12:00) + X&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; being a constant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; tickets will be available until &lt;strong&gt;Tuesday 12:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After which the registration is closed. We wish to avoid throwing away food, on one hand, as well as respect those who have reserved place and avoid running out of food, on the other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entry to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/06oOA&#34;&gt;Booking.com building&lt;/a&gt; will be made available via Security personnel to those people who will be listed by the eventbrite registration. We will not be able to have last moment registrants; we will not collect money at the entrance; no credit cards accepted at the doorway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;d like to attend the community dinner, please &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/community-dinner-bookingcom-tickets-17901675393&#34;&gt;register&lt;/a&gt; now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FYI Percona has arranged for boats to make the travel from the conference venue to Booking.com (no registration required, but room limited on those boats as well).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now ain&#39;t I being dramatic here. &lt;em&gt;So happy&lt;/em&gt; to see everyone here in Amsterdam in a few days!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live Amsterdam: Community Dinner, Sep. 22nd</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/08/13/percona-live-amsterdam-community-dinner-sep-22nd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2015 19:21:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/08/13/percona-live-amsterdam-community-dinner-sep-22nd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Keeping up with tradition, there will be a community event held at the upcoming &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/europe-amsterdam-2015/&#34;&gt;Percona Live Europe: Amsterdam 2015&lt;/a&gt; conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.booking.com&#34;&gt;Booking.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; will be hosting the event at the company&#39;s headquarters in the heart of Amsterdam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will hold a community dinner (dish selection, includes vegetarian; beverages will be served) in our caffeteria and hope to add some spicy activities to the event!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Space is limited, and tickets can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/community-dinner-bookingcom-tickets-17901675393&#34;&gt;purchased via Eventbrite&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Daniël van Eeden and Jean-François Gagné for their work in making this happen!&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Tuesday, September 22, 2015 from 6:30 PM to 10:00 PM (CEST)&lt;br /&gt;
Herengracht 597, 1017 CE&lt;br /&gt;
Amsterdam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Location: &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/06oOA&#34;&gt;https://goo.gl/maps/06oOA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walking route from conference venue: &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/Ocptu&#34;&gt;https://goo.gl/maps/Ocptu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe style=&#34;border: 0;&#34; src=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m28!1m12!1m3!1d9743.703328920092!2d4.896253511753787!3d52.37176484148813!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!4m13!3e2!4m5!1s0x47c609af134a69db%3A0xa010dcc86a7b3f04!2sM%C3%B6venpick+Hotel+Amsterdam+City+Centre%2C+Piet+Heinkade%2C+Amsterdam!3m2!1d52.3778973!2d4.9142855999999995!4m5!1s0x47c609959752b349%3A0x7d8516d374ac50cd!2sBooking.com%2C+Herengracht+597%2C+1017+CE+Amsterdam!3m2!1d52.3656116!2d4.8984594!5e0!3m2!1sen!2snl!4v1439486186201&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;450&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;awesome-mysql&#34; curated list created, open for pull requests</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/04/28/awesome-mysql-curated-list-created-open-for-pull-requests/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2015 14:48:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/04/28/awesome-mysql-curated-list-created-open-for-pull-requests/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Following up on popular &lt;em&gt;&#34;awesome-*&#34;&lt;/em&gt; lists (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vinta/awesome-python&#34;&gt;awesome-python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/avelino/awesome-go&#34;&gt;awesome-golang&lt;/a&gt; etc.), I&#39;ve created the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/shlomi-noach/awesome-mysql&#34;&gt;awesome-mysql&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; curated list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a list of technologies (and resources) in and around MySQL, and means to serve as a place to find reliable software and info. I recently happened to notice there are some tools I&#39;m familiar with that are unknown to others; tools unknown to me that are in good use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list is naturally and intentionally incomplete. I wish this to be a community based creation; so I put some categories and some tools. I left many out, &lt;em&gt;deliberatey&lt;/em&gt;. Please assist by filling in the missing projects, tools, libraries! Additions gladly accepted via pull-requests. Do note the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/shlomi-noach/awesome-mysql/blob/master/CONTRIBUTING.md&#34;&gt;contribution guidelines&lt;/a&gt; (somewhat lengthy, I apologize).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will moderate FUDs, promotional, commercials etc., and otherwise it may take some days for me to merge requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work is licensed under the &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live 2015: Reflections; the Apache CCLA offer</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/04/18/percona-live-2015-reflections-the-apache-ccla-offer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2015 03:11:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/04/18/percona-live-2015-reflections-the-apache-ccla-offer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facebook, Google, Twitter, LinkedIn, Alibaba, MariaDB, Percona team up and offer Oracle all public changes under the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apache.org/licenses/cla-corporate.txt&#34;&gt;Apache CCLA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read again please.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My one word summary of this is: Romantic. In the most positive sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: I am not a lawyer; this is my understanding of the current status and of the offer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summarizing the deal: the teams participating with WebScaleSQL would like to push code upstream. Current legal issues limit their options. Existing patches/contributions from Percona &amp;amp; MariaDB are licensed by GPLv2, which Oracle cannot import as it distributes a commercial, closed source, edition, in addition to its open source MySQL community edition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what happens is that there is a lot of free code, great patches, new features out there, that are only available via MariaDB or WebscaleSQL or Percona Server, but not in the Oracle MySQL code base. This, in turn, means Oracle re-implements many features originating from said companies. And, more importantly, said companies need to routinely rebase their code on new Oracle releases, repeating tedious work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The offer is that Oracle agrees to the Apache CCLA as a license by which it would be able to incorporate contributions. Oracle would then be able to use incorporated code in both open source and commercial edition. Oracle will choose what code to incorporate; hopefully many patches will be accepted upstream, and the community will benefit from a rich featureset, rapid developed MySQL server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly a lot of work, persuasion, lawyer time, discussions etc. have been invested in this effort. I would like to add my humble &lt;strong&gt;+1/like/favorite/whathaveyou&lt;/strong&gt;. You may add yours by letting Oracle know your opinion on the subject. Media tools are great for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Community Awards 2015: the Winners</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/04/18/mysql-community-awards-2015-the-winners/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2015 02:19:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/04/18/mysql-community-awards-2015-the-winners/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The MySQL Community Awards initiative is an effort to acknowledge and thank individuals and corporates for their contributions to the MySQL ecosystem. It is a from-the-community, by-the-community and for-the-community effort. The committee is composed of an independent group of community members of different orientation and opinion, themselves past winners or known contributors to the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2015 community awards were presented on April 15rd, 2015, during the community event at the Percona Live conference. The winners are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Community Contributor of the year 2015&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Daniël van Eeden&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;Daniël has done great work on MySQL security and has continued to fantastically support MySQL User Group.NL. He has also logged a lot of bugs (and submitted patches), across all sorts of different MySQL products and has done a great deal to help improve the quality of MySQL.Daniël consistently provides extremely good feedback, on a wide range of features and products, from MySQL server security, through InnoDB, partitioning, and even on other products such MySQL Enterprise Backup and MySQL Enterprise Monitor. His bugs are always reported with a high quality, and many times he even includes a contribution to fix those bugs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Justin Swanhart&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;Justin has worked tirelessly for the past few years on some amazing projects of his own design, Shard-Query and Flexviews. Cross shard aggregation is an extremely complex thing to get right, and Shard-Query takes an interesting approach at this. Flexviews provides a materialized view framework, which is something that MySQL lacks to many people&#39;s annoyance. Additionally Justin has also built some performance_schema related tools, reported many MySQL bugs, and has been a public speaker about MySQL in &#34;can do&#34; style.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Morgan Tocker&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;In his day job, Morgan is Community Manager at Oracle. While some of his community interaction has been because of his job, he has gone far and beyond his corporate responsibilities. He is one of the most prolific writers on the MySQL Planet, he has been the most public face of MySQL, and he is always asking for feedback and showing a sincere concern for the Open Source community.For example, Morgan’s community polls on what defaults should be changed in MySQL 5.7 put some of the MySQL product decision making directly into the hands of the community. He is a key player on keeping the community and the MySQL developers at Oracle in touch with each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Application of the year 2015&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sys schema&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As PERFORMANCE_SCHEMA matured in the MySQL ecosystem, Mark Leith identified the need to condense its information around user-friendliness and visibility.  Out of this, the ps_helper and eventually MySQL SYS projects were born. This actively-developed, one-man project has become a standard integration in the MySQL distribution today.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VividCortex&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
VividCortex brings fresh and challenging ideas to the monitoring space, originally targeting MySQL. It provides near realtime information that was previously deemed unattainable through aggressive sampling and original statistical formulas that is raising the bar for monitoring high performance data stores at scale.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Corporate Contributor of the year 2015&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WebScaleSQL Contributors: Facebook, Google, Twitter, LinkedIn, Alibaba&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It’s a common misconception, but WebScaleSQL is not a competitor to MySQL – it is strongly rooted in Oracle’s MySQL and closely follows its “upstream” MySQL codebase. Instead, it is intended as a place for several companies that were already collaborating on scalability improvements in MySQL to do so in a quicker and more succinct manner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congrats to all winners!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Committee members are:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baron Schwartz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colin Charles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frederic Descamps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geoffrey Anderson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giuseppe Maxia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marc Delisle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark Leith&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Philip Stoev&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ronald Bradford&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Santiago Lertora&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;Jeremy Cole &lt;em&gt;(Secretary)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shlomi Noach &lt;em&gt;(Secretary)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Special thanks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to this year&#39;s anonymous sponsor for donating the goblets!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to Colin Charles for acquiring and transporting the goblets!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to Santiago Lertora for working out &lt;a href=&#34;http://mysqlawards.org/&#34;&gt;the new swards website&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/community-awards-2015.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-7214&#34; src=&#34;/blog/blog/assets/community-awards-2015.png&#34; alt=&#34;community-awards-2015&#34; width=&#34;843&#34; height=&#34;446&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Community Awards 2015: Call for Nominations!</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/02/06/mysql-community-awards-2015-call-for-nominations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2015 21:37:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/02/06/mysql-community-awards-2015-call-for-nominations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;2015&lt;/strong&gt; MySQL Community Awards event will take place, as usual, in Santa Clara, during the Percona Live MySQL Conference &amp;amp; Expo, April 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MySQL Community Awards is a community based initiative. The idea is to publicly recognize contributors to the MySQL ecosystem. The entire process of discussing, voting and awarding is controlled by an independent group of community members, typically based of past winners or their representatives, as well as known contributors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a self-appointed, self-declared, self-making-up-the-rules-as-it-goes committee. It is also very aware of the importance of the community; a no-nonsense, non-political, adhering to tradition, self criticizing committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Call for Nominations is open. We are seeking the community’s assistance in nominating candidates in the following categories:&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Community Contributor of the year 2015&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a personal award; a winner would a person who has made contribution to the MySQL ecosystem. This could be via development, advocating, blogging, speaking, supporting, etc. All things go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Application of the year 2015&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An application, project, product etc. which supports the MySQL ecosystem by either contributing code, complementing its behaviour, supporting its use, etc. This could range from a one man open source project to a large scale social service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Corporate Contributor of the year 2015&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A company who made contribution to the MySQL ecosystem. This might be a corporate which released major open source code; one that advocates for MySQL; one that help out community members by... anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a list of previous winners, please see &lt;a href=&#34;http://openlife.cc/blogs/2012/february/mysql-hall-fame&#34;&gt;MySQL Hall of Fame&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Process of nomination and voting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone can nominate anyone. When nominating, please make sure to provide a brief explanation on why the candidate is eligible to get the award. Make a good case!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee will review all nominations and vote; it typically takes two rounds of votes to pick the winners, and a lot of discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be &lt;em&gt;up to&lt;/em&gt; three winners in each category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods of nomination:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send en email to &lt;strong&gt;mysql.community.awards&lt;/strong&gt;@&lt;strong&gt;gmail.com&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comment to this post&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assuming you can provide a reasonable description in &lt;strong&gt;140&lt;/strong&gt; characters, tweet your nomination at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=MySQLAwards&amp;amp;src=typd&amp;amp;f=realtime&#34;&gt;#MySQLAwards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please submit your nominations no later than &lt;strong&gt;Saturday, February 28, 2015&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The committee&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Members of the committee are: Baron Schwartz, Colin Charles, Domas Mituzas, Fredric Descamps, Geoffrey Anderson, Giuseppe Maxia, Marc Delisle, Mark Leith, Philip Stoev, Ronald Bradford, Santiago Lertora. A couple additional members pending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Cole and myself (Shlomi Noach) are acting as co-secretaries; we will be non-voting (except for breaking ties).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee communicates throughout the nomination and voting process to exchange views and opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The awards&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awards are traditionally (as in this year) donated by some party whose identity remains secret. Thank you, kind sponsor!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Support&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a community effort; we ask for your support in spreading the word and of course in nominating candidates. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Community Awards 2014: the Winners</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/04/04/mysql-community-awards-2014-the-winners/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2014 19:17:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/04/04/mysql-community-awards-2014-the-winners/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The MySQL Community Awards initiative is an effort to acknowledge and thank individuals and corporates for their contributions to the MySQL ecosystem. It is a from-the-community, by-the-community and for-the-community effort. The committee is composed of an independent group of community members of different orientation and opinion, themselves past winners or known contributors to the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2014 community awards were presented on April 3rd, 2014, during the community event at the Percona Live conference. The winners are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Community Contributor of the year 2014&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colin Charles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Colin&#39;s list of service to the MySQL Community goes back almost 10 years. He was a community engineer starting in 2005, chaired some of the O&#39;Reilly MySQL conferences, ran the MySQL projects for Google Summer of Code. As a partner and Chief Evangelist for Monty program, he continues to promote and grow the MySQL ecosystem. Though it&#39;s his job, he goes above and beyond, driven by his passion for open source and MySQL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frédéric Descamps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Frederic organizes the MySQL &amp;amp; Friends Devroom at FOSDEM every year. He worked towards making a true community driven event participated by all key players. in 2014 the MySQL &amp;amp; Friends devroom also presented a shared booth/stand regrouping Oracle, MariaDB/SkySQL and Percona engineers and developers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geoffrey Anderson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Geoffrey is organizor &amp;amp; moderator at DBHangops: a bi-weekly community hangout discussing all things MySQL. The hangouts are free to join, and are streamed live and stored for later playback via YouTube.&lt;br /&gt;
Geoffrey works to provide with content, and leads the hangouts with good spirit. DBHangOps makes for a good knowledge sharing media.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Application of the year 2014&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Galera&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Galera provides MySQL with synchronous replication, offering a long time sought for High Availability solution for MySQL. It is fast becoming one of the main product/technology everyone is building next-gen businesses around. It is an important part of the renaissance of what&#39;s next for the &#34;ecosystem&#34;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Random Query Generator&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Random Query Generator has found hundreds of problems with its random generation of queries, because often the most serious bugs are outside of developers&#39; expectations and their test cases. Engineers who work on MySQL and its derivatives have been able to vastly improve the quality of the database because of it. Random Query Generator has positively effected every single user in the MySQL ecosystem, mostly without them even knowing it.&lt;br /&gt;
RQG was originally created by Philip Stoev, and has attracted further contributors over the years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Corporate Contributor of the year 2014&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oracle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Oracle has continued to show its commitment to MySQL with the 5.6 release and work in progress on 5.7. MySQL 5.6 might be the best release ever with significant improvements for InnoDB and replication (performance, GTIDs, parallel apply) including significant changes from the community. The 5.7 release has equally high goals for making replication better (enhanced semi-sync) and making InnoDB faster on big multi-core servers. We also appreciate the continued involvement, excellence and passion of the support and community teams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BinLogic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
BinLogic has been a great steward of the MySQL Community in one of the fastest growing technology hubs, Latin America. BinLogic created the MySQL, NoSQL and Cloud Solutions day in 2012 and repeated the event in 2013, drawing in notable speakers from the community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congrats to all winners!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Committee members are:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baron Schwartz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domas Mituzas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gerry Narvaja&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giuseppe Maxia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jeremy Cole&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Justin Swanhart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marc Delisle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark Leith&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ronald Bradford&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sarah Novotny&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sheeri K. Cabral&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tim Callaghan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark Callaghan (co-secretary)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shlomi Noach (co-secretary)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also wish to recognize and thank &lt;a href=&#34;http://openlife.cc&#34;&gt;Henrik Ingo&lt;/a&gt; for initiating and promoting this process throughout the past years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[UPDATE] To elaborate, the community awards pre-date back to &lt;strong&gt;2005&lt;/strong&gt;, where awards were given by MySQL AB, and later Sun Microsystems. Arjen Lentz, Jay Pipes, Colin Charles, Giuseppe Maxia and Lenz Grimmer are all past organizers of the community awards.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Community Awards 2014: Call for Nominations!</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/02/09/mysql-community-awards-2014-call-for-nominations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 08:00:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/02/09/mysql-community-awards-2014-call-for-nominations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;2014&lt;/strong&gt; MySQL Community Awards event will take place, as usual, in Santa Clara, April 2014, during the Percona Live MySQL Conference &amp;amp; Expo (currently scheduled at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/program/schedule/sessions-day-2&#34;&gt;Thursday, April 3rd 2014&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MySQL Community Awards is a community based initiative. The idea is to publicly recognize contributors to the MySQL ecosystem. The entire process of discussing, voting and awarding is controlled by an independent group of community members, typically based of past winners or their representatives, as well as known contributors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a self-appointed, self-declared, self-making-up-the-rules-as-it-goes committee. It is also very aware of the importance of the community; a no-nonsense, non-political, adhering to tradition, self criticizing committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Call for Nominations is open. We are seeking the community’s assistance in nominating candidates in the following categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Community Contributor of the year 2014&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a personal award; a winner would a person who has made contribution to the MySQL ecosystem. This could be via development, advocating, blogging, speaking, supporting, etc. All things go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Application of the year 2014&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An application, project, product etc. which supports the MySQL ecosystem by either contributing code, complementing its behaviour, supporting its use, etc. This could range from a one man open source project to a large scale social service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Corporate Contributor of the year 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A company who made contribution to the MySQL ecosystem. This might be a corporate which released major open source code; one that advocates for MySQL; one that help out community members by... anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see the criteria are flexible. They all boil down to one thing: what gain the nominees provide the community with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please also see the &lt;a href=&#34;http://openlife.cc/blogs/2013/january/call-nominations-mysql-community-awards-2013&#34;&gt;2013 Call for Nominations&lt;/a&gt; by Henrik Ingo for more insights; also note the &lt;a href=&#34;http://openlife.cc/blogs/2012/february/mysql-hall-fame&#34;&gt;MySQL Hall of Fame&lt;/a&gt; (up to 2012) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://openlife.cc/blogs/2013/april/mysql-community-awards-2013-and-winners-are&#34;&gt;2013 winners&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Process of nomination and voting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone can nominate anyone. When nominating, please make sure to provide a brief explanation on why the candidate is eligible to get the award. Make a good case!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee will review all nominations and vote; it typically takes two rounds of votes to pick the winners, and a lot of discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be &lt;em&gt;up to&lt;/em&gt; three winners in each category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods of nomination:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send en email to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mysql.community.awards&lt;/strong&gt;@&lt;strong&gt;gmail.com&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comment to this post&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assuming you can provide a reasonable description in &lt;strong&gt;140&lt;/strong&gt; characters, tweet your nomination at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=MySQLAwards&amp;amp;src=typd&amp;amp;f=realtime&#34;&gt;#MySQLAwards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please submit your nominations no later than &lt;strong&gt;Sunday, &lt;del&gt;January&lt;/del&gt; February 23, 2014&lt;/strong&gt;. (whoops)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The committee&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Callaghan and myself (Shlomi Noach) are acting as co-secretaries; we will be non-voting (except for breaking ties). Members are: Baron Schwartz, Domas Mituzas, Gerry Narvaja, Giuseppe Maxia, Jeremy Cole, Justin Swanhart, Marc Delisle, Mark Leith, Ronald Bradford, Sarah Novotny, Sheeri K. Cabral, Tim Callaghan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee communicates throughout the nomination and voting process to exchange views and opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The awards&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awards are traditionally (as in this year) donated by some party, who&#39;s identity remains secret.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Support&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a community effort; we ask for your support in spreading the word and of course in nominating candidates. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live 2014 schedule released; BoF and Lightning Talks Call for Papers continues</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/01/16/percona-live-2014-schedule-released-bof-and-lightning-talks-call-for-papers-continues/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 11:01:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/01/16/percona-live-2014-schedule-released-bof-and-lightning-talks-call-for-papers-continues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The complete tutorial &amp;amp; session schedule for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/&#34;&gt;Percona Live MySQL Conference &amp;amp; Expo 2014&lt;/a&gt; is released. This schedule offers both a sense of achievement as well as a sense of regret; for I believe the schedule is very good, and yet some good proposals had to be left out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an inevitable result of a conference that is popular and receives far more proposals than can fit within the time frames. This conference offers &lt;strong&gt;96&lt;/strong&gt; session slots and &lt;strong&gt;16&lt;/strong&gt; 3-hour tutorial slots. We got well over &lt;strong&gt;300&lt;/strong&gt; proposals -- I&#39;m not even sure how to count them -- and they just can&#39;t all fit in. My sincere apologies to all those left out. A proposal of mine was just rejected yesterday from another conference; I can sympathize and empathize with all turned down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of our interest in having a diversity of talks and speakers, we have promoted talks by less frequent speakers and newly presenting companies. We are happy to grow the community!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although titled &#34;Percona Live&#34;, this conference&#39;s program is managed by a diverse and independent committee. We had good discussions and some very good thinking and advice were offered. I&#39;m happy to acknowledge and thank the committee members:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cédric Peintre, Dailymotion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giuseppe Maxia, Continuent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ivan Zoratti, SkySQL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jay Janssen, Percona&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jeremy Cole, Google&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laine Campbell, PalominoDB (now Blackbird, congrats!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liz van Dijk, Percona&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roland Bouman, Pentaho&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tim Callaghan, Tokutek&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Todd Farmer, Oracle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;myself, Outbrain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the schedule I&#39;m as always eager to attend many more sessions than I can; until I get more replicas of myself, It&#39;s again down to choosing between multiple prominent talks at each time slot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to all those who submitted a proposal! (It&#39;s cool, just saying)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Birds of a Feather, Lightning Talks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Call for papers continues! You are encouraged to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/user&#34;&gt;submit your proposals&lt;/a&gt; until end of January. These proposals are reviewed by the committee, and eventually chosen and scheduled by Giuseppe Maxia. See also:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://datacharmer.blogspot.co.il/2013/11/call-for-papers-with-lightning-talks.html&#34;&gt;Call for papers (with lightning talks): Percona Live MySQL Conference 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://datacharmer.blogspot.co.il/2013/12/submissions-at-percona-live-santa-clara.html&#34;&gt;Submissions at Percona Live Santa Clara 2014 and Lightning talks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why a professional conference must have a committee, and what that committee does</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/12/14/why-a-professional-conference-must-have-a-committee-and-what-that-committee-does/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 11:11:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/12/14/why-a-professional-conference-must-have-a-committee-and-what-that-committee-does/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What exactly is it that a conference committee does? This post comes as response to a comment on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mysqlperformanceblog.com/2013/12/11/percona-live-2014-conference-sneak-peek/&#34;&gt;A sneak peek at the Percona Live MySQL Conference &amp;amp; Expo 2014&lt;/a&gt;, reading:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Why the same committee each year? Community should vote on proposals and committee should just work schedule,etc.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll pick the glove and shed some light into the work of the committee. While this specific comment related to the Percona Live conference, I trust that my opinions expressed below apply just as well to any (technical?) professional conference; the point below can equally apply to conferences from Oracle MySQL Connect, O&#39;Reilly Velocity to FOSDEM &amp;amp; PyCon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can sum up the entire answer with one word: &#34;Discussion&#34;. For a breakdown, please read through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;First, what&#39;s not feasible with community-based voting, and what looks very wrong&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why not open up a voting system and let the community do the rating? I always disliked the &#34;send an SMS to this number to vote for X&#34; approach. It is so unbalanced and unreliable: if I were to submit a proposal describing how my company invented/develops/uses X to do great things, I can expect my co-workers to vote for me. In fact, my company would possibly ask my co-workers to do so. I stand a better chance if I work in a large company; less so in a small company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anonymous votes tend to be touched by politics. I could vote for my company, against a competing product, for my friends, against people I dislike, and none the wiser. We can take away anonymity, which means my votes will be public, which means they are visible to all. In which case my ranking will be affected by what people I rate would think of me; which means my rating would not be based on strictly professional/technical grounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before we drop into this endless pit, let&#39;s consider: will I, as a KMyPyVelocirails community member, really engage in reviewing over 300 submissions? How many members of my community would take so many hours of their time to do so? Let me clarify, this is a part-time job. It requires time, and it requires a mindset. I&#39;m guessing here that you cannot count on everyone rating all talks. Some more prominent talks will be reviewed by more people, others may be left little to not reviewed in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of a purely community based rating is romantic and beautiful, but not feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there&#39;s the &lt;em&gt;discussion&lt;/em&gt;. Let&#39;s look at some of the things the committee is engaged in to clarify.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Duties, responsibility and actions of a conference committee&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following discussion cannot be an exhaustive description of a committee&#39;s work, but it can give a good glimpse into its scope. We begin with the commitment the members take upon themselves: to invest their time and will in the committee&#39;s duties. Once you join in, you are expected to work and deliver.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The duties of the reviewing committee extend beyond reviewing the proposals -- though this duty is the most critical of all, as it serves the basis for all others. So let&#39;s describe this first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Reviewing the proposals&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reviewing papers is more than rating them (1-5 stars). We also comment and share our opinion. Members typically explain why they rated the way they did, especially on low rating. Our ratings and comments are visible to other members, and they can react on these. For example, I can disagree with one&#39;s comments and counter-comment myself. We can continue this discussion in our mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might throw in our experience in attending the same talk in the past. Was it good? Was it bad? Yes, it matters; we want the conference to be successful, and our personal experience is something we bring to the table. We might have some inside knowledge about an emerging technology, or speakers may share with us such knowledge in private section (&lt;em&gt;&#34;By the time this talk is given, this project will have been released as open source&#34;&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may suggest improvements: &lt;em&gt;&#34;Better make this tutorial 3 hours instead of 6&#34;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&#34;Should include this topic as well&#34;&lt;/em&gt;. We might (and sometimes do) approach speakers to refine their submissions if we think they can make for good sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can express our true professional opinion on proposals. We wouldn&#39;t always want to share in public; this private discussion works for the benefit of all - there is no reason to suspect we use fluttery nor insults. We just say what we think within our small group -- and still be prepared for backfire from our peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, wait. By which guidelines do we vote? Before we even start rating, we set the very basic guidelines, such as &#34;what content are we looking for; what&#39;s this conference about, what it is not, what are the rules for rating, ...&#34;. Can I rate talks submitted by my colleagues? Would that be unfair? But if so, am I allowed to rate our competitors? Wouldn&#39;t &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; be unfair as well? Is there an end to it? We set these rules up front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Meta&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the reviewing process we collect meta-data about the submitted papers. Do we find content that is missing? Do we have enough &#34;beginner&#34; talks?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some speakers submit 5-6 talks, in the hope than one or two make it through. But they don&#39;t really intend to submit 5 or 6 talks if all happen to get approved. And the committee also prefers a variety of speakers. The committee (or committee chairman) reaches to those speakers to understand better their limitations. We can therefore reject talks based on high submission number per speaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We typically very quickly stumble upon the issue of overlapping content. Some topics are proposed again and again by multiple speakers. We take notes and balance the figures. We sometimes reject talks not because the abstracts are bad, but because we have so many other competing talks on same topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may choose to promote an open source product. We may be passionate about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we do reach a conclusion that some content is missing, we may pursue the issue by contacting speakers or potential speakers to submit papers on the subject. We may contact specific companies or speakers that we know would provide good value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We make backup plans: speakers cancel; some don&#39;t get Visas, some fall ill. We make a &#34;Waitlist&#34; of sessions and verify with speakers that they would be able to provide them upon request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speakers may have personal limitations, e.g. only being able to attend on this and that days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Non reviewing tasks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are further engaged in shaping the general shape of the conference. The organizers consult with us on various topics. I guess this really depends on the nature of the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see from all the above, this is far from just rating all the talks and picking the &#34;top &lt;strong&gt;100&lt;/strong&gt; talks&#34;. There are a lot of constraints, limitations, contradictions, and issues to go through. This cannot be an automated &#34;community vote&#34; thing. And the moment you put someone at the position of making decision, you&#39;re effectively reinventing the committee.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>common_schema roadmap thoughts</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/07/22/common_schema-roadmap-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2013 14:36:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/07/22/common_schema-roadmap-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m happy with &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://code.google.com/p/common-schema/&#34;&gt;common_schema&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;; it is in fact a tool I use myself on an almost daily basis. I&#39;m also happy to see that it gains traction; which is why I&#39;m exposing a little bit of my thoughts on general future development. I&#39;d love to get feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Supported versions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this moment, &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; supports MySQL &amp;gt;= &lt;strong&gt;5.1&lt;/strong&gt;, all variants. This includes &lt;strong&gt;5.5&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;5.6&lt;/strong&gt;, MySQL, Percona Server &amp;amp; MariaDB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.1&lt;/strong&gt; is today past end of line, and I&#39;m really missing the &lt;strong&gt;SIGNAL&lt;/strong&gt;/&lt;strong&gt;RESIGNAL&lt;/strong&gt; syntax that I would like to use; I can do in the meanwhile with version-specific code such as &lt;strong&gt;/*!50500 ... */&lt;/strong&gt;. Nevertheless, I&#39;m wondering whether I will eventually have to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support different branches of &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; (one that supports &lt;strong&gt;5.1&lt;/strong&gt;, one that supports &amp;gt;= &lt;strong&gt;5.5&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stop support for &lt;strong&gt;5.1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course community-wise, the former is preferred; but I have limited resources, so I would like to make a quick poll here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[poll id=&#34;3&#34;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll use the poll&#39;s results as a &lt;em&gt;vague idea of what people use and want&lt;/em&gt;. Or please use comments below to sound your voice!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;rdebug&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a crazy jump at providing a &lt;a href=&#34;http://common-schema.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/common_schema/doc/html/rdebug.html&#34;&gt;stored routine debugger and debugging API&lt;/a&gt;. From some talk I made I don&#39;t see this getting traction. For the time being, I don&#39;t see that I will concentrate my efforts on this. Actually it is almost complete. You can step-into, step-out, step-over, set breakpoints, read variables, modify variables -- it&#39;s pretty cool.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But someone will eventually have to write a GUI front-end for this (eclipse/IntelliJ/whatever); I know not many will use a command line approach for a debugger. I also know I&#39;m not going to write the GUI front-end. So the API is there, let&#39;s see how it rolls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;QueryScript&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will keep on improving &lt;a href=&#34;http://common-schema.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/common_schema/doc/html/query_script.html&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;QueryScript&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and in particular split, error handling, and otherwise simplification of common tasks. I have no doubt QueryScript goes the right way: I just see how easy it is to solve complex problems with a QueryScript one-liner. Other bullets on my TODO for QueryScript:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Script tracking (a semi-debugging mechanism, which allows one to recognize status of script)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Message passing to scripts (again, a semi-debugger approach)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Error recovery; ability to resume script from point of failure or point of suspension. I have plenty use cases for that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;performance_schema&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will most probably include parts of Mark Leith&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.markleith.co.uk/ps_helper/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ps_helper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is released under &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wtfpl.net/&#34;&gt;a permissive license&lt;/a&gt;, and otherwise draw ideas from his work. I&#39;m happy to learn parts of &lt;em&gt;ps_helper&lt;/em&gt; were influenced by &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Hosting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; will most probably move out of Google Code; by Jan 2014 there will no longer be a &#34;Downloads&#34; section, and I really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;, want there to be a &lt;em&gt;&#34;Downloads&#34;&lt;/em&gt; section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could go LaunchPad, GitHub, BitBucket (they don&#39;t have &lt;em&gt;&#34;Downloads&#34;&lt;/em&gt; sections, either, do they?), other; any advice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;World domination&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep. This is still &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt;&#39;s goal. More seriously, I would want to see it installed on every single MySQL server instance. Then I would control your fate. bwahahaha!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more seriously, if you are a happy user, please do pass the word. I can only blog so much and present so much; there are no financing resources for this project, and I need all the help I can get in promoting &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt;. Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>common_schema &amp; openark-kit in the media: #DBHangOps, OurSQL</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/06/26/common_schema-openark-kit-in-the-media-dbhangops-oursql/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2013 21:46:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/06/26/common_schema-openark-kit-in-the-media-dbhangops-oursql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4&gt;#DBHangOps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of joining into &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DBHangops&#34;&gt;@DBHangOps&lt;/a&gt; today, and speak about &lt;a href=&#34;https://code.google.com/p/common-schema/&#34;&gt;common_schema&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.google.com/p/openarkkit/&#34;&gt;openark-kit&lt;/a&gt;. What was meant to be a 15 minute session turned to be 50 -- sorry, people, I don&#39;t talk as much at home, but when it comes to my pet projects...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also realized I was missing on a great event: DBHangOps is a hangout where you can chat and discuss MySQL &amp;amp; related technologies with friends and colleagues, with whom you typically only meet at conferences. I will certainly want to attend future events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to John Cesario and Geoffrey Anderson who invited me to talk, and to the friends and familiar faces who attended; I was happy to talk about my work, and very interested in hearing about how it&#39;s being put to use. We also had time to discuss &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.markleith.co.uk/ps_helper/&#34;&gt;ps_helper&lt;/a&gt; with no other than Mark Leith!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video is &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DBHangops/status/349965939690835970&#34;&gt;available on Twitter/YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;OurSQL&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;openark-kit&lt;/em&gt; has also been &lt;a href=&#34;http://technocation.org/content/oursql-episode-143%3A-biblical-tools&#34;&gt;featured on the OurSQL podcast&lt;/a&gt; by Sheeri &amp;amp; Gerry, who did great coverage of some tools. I will disclose that more is to come; I&#39;m happy this is in capable hands and look further to hear the next episode!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impressions from Percona Live 2013</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/04/26/impressions-from-percona-live-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2013 18:37:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/04/26/impressions-from-percona-live-2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the airport, trying to sum up my impressions from Percona Live 2013 conference in Santa Clara.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woo! Hard to sum up four excellent days. Shall I review the great talks I&#39;ve been to? The keynotes? The well organized events?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know what, skip it. There was ONE thing that overshadowed everything. It was the ONE thing for me that was the pure essence of the conference and its greatest joy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meeting and talking to a great many great people!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was fortunate to meet up with so many people; none that I planned; things just went in such way that I engaged in so many conversations with so many people. I found myself talking about hamsters, peacocks, living in the village, living in the city, working from home, commute, relocation, working with your spouse, life in Israel, life in Argentina, prisons in the US, having many children, gun control, politics (heaven forbid!), fruit, vegetables, breakfasts, open source, community, buying (non-expensive) presents to your kids, new ventures, zen, philosophy, capitalism, socialism, books, being who you are, weddings, Java, scripting, NoSQL, how to contribute to an open source project, ... the list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was &#34;adopted&#34; by the PalominoDB team at Pedro&#39;s, crash-partied on Pythian fellows, talked technical (or non technical) with Tokutek guys, meeting up with Oracle people (finally I get the faces behind the names!); the companies do not matter, I&#39;m just throwing in names. The &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; are awesome! Representing their companies on the technical side, and being purely interesting people on the personal side, I met with men and women from all over the community. Apologies: impossible to list all nor account for!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s great to have a place and time where we all meet together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bottom line? I am fortunate to have my current profession: I enjoy my work, and the people I meet are fantastic and of the highest quality!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks all with whom I&#39;ve met, and for all of those with whom I haven&#39;t had the chance to speak: &lt;em&gt;see you next time!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live 2013 schedule released!</title>
      <link>/blog/2012/12/20/percona-live-2013-schedule-released/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2012 16:33:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2012/12/20/percona-live-2013-schedule-released/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m happy to report the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2013/program/schedule/sessions-day-1&#34;&gt;release of the program schedule&lt;/a&gt; for the next Percona Live event, April &lt;strong&gt;2013&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you can see there are still some &#34;TODO&#34;s, and minor scheduling changes still to go, the overall reviewing process is complete, and the schedule is sound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2013/conference-committee&#34;&gt;committee&lt;/a&gt; has reviewed over &lt;strong&gt;250&lt;/strong&gt; submissions in total, sessions and tutorials. It took two months to review the sessions and finalize the schedule. There were very good submissions, and it wasn&#39;t till I started building the schedule that I realized just how many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know the feeling: you&#39;re at a conference, and there&#39;s this time slot where you just can&#39;t make up your mind which session to attend. As it turns out, anyway I look at it, I get this at each and every single time slot in this schedule. Hopefully all attendees should feel similarly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What can you expect to find in the Santa Clara, April conference?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, we get variety of topics. First day is tutorials, which I already &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/mysql/percona-live-2013-tutorials-schedule-released&#34;&gt;mentioned&lt;/a&gt;, followed by three days of sessions and keynotes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some topics you can guess: always place for good backup practice, performance optimizations for your InnoDB deployment, good indexing strategies and more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open source and emerging technologies are well covered: from Tungsten, Galera/Percona XtraDB Cluster, NDB Cluster to MHA, HAProxy, Hadoop, Percona Toolkit and more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MariaDB has good coverage, as well as Percona Server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scale topics such as sharding, building large deployments,Big Data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud is well represented, too. Deployments on Amazon, Google Cloud, OpenStack, SkySQL Cloud Data Suite; interesting content on virtualization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimizer, better queries, query evaluation plans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replication, of course, is as always a hot topic, this year in particular due to anticipated 5.6 release&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking of 5.6, a lot of content on that, too. PERFORMANCE_SCHEMA, InnoDB, partitions, GIS and more...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case studies: can you do without them? Get to hear how big companies used product/project X, what it took to make it work, how it helped them grow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chance to get up to speed on third party solutions: Akiban, Tokutek, ScaleDB...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hardware: SSDs are all the rage. How do you nest choose and configure your hardware and deployment?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Best practices, security, monitoring, NoSQL...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And, I can&#39;t list everything, but a LOT of good, unique content!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will write some more on specific sessions I find that are of unique interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, this is my first time acting as committee chairman, and so much of this work was new to me, and I got to learn it on the fly. Thankfully, the committee is composed of experienced conference veterans, not to mention experts, who gave good advice. I was happy to ask for their advice and happy to accept. I wish to thank the committee members for their kindness and openness! (That doesn&#39;t mean I&#39;m buying you all your beer though!)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>