<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Perconalive on code.openark.org</title>
    <link>/blog/tag/perconalive/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Perconalive on code.openark.org</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2015 14:14:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/blog/tag/perconalive/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live Amsterdam: Community Dinner, last updates</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/percona-live-amsterdam-community-dinner-last-updates/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2015 14:14:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/percona-live-amsterdam-community-dinner-last-updates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Registration for the Percona Live Amsterdam conference &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/community-dinner-bookingcom-tickets-17901675393&#34;&gt;community dinner at Booking.com&lt;/a&gt; is ongoing. Please note the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By Monday noon the kitchen will make the necessary purchasing. At this time we will have to give them a number, which we will not exceed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number we will give them is &lt;strong&gt;$(number of registrants Monday 12:00) + X&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; being a constant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; tickets will be available until &lt;strong&gt;Tuesday 12:00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After which the registration is closed. We wish to avoid throwing away food, on one hand, as well as respect those who have reserved place and avoid running out of food, on the other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entry to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/06oOA&#34;&gt;Booking.com building&lt;/a&gt; will be made available via Security personnel to those people who will be listed by the eventbrite registration. We will not be able to have last moment registrants; we will not collect money at the entrance; no credit cards accepted at the doorway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;d like to attend the community dinner, please &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/community-dinner-bookingcom-tickets-17901675393&#34;&gt;register&lt;/a&gt; now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FYI Percona has arranged for boats to make the travel from the conference venue to Booking.com (no registration required, but room limited on those boats as well).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now ain&#39;t I being dramatic here. &lt;em&gt;So happy&lt;/em&gt; to see everyone here in Amsterdam in a few days!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at Percona Live Amsterdam: Orchestrator</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/speaking-at-percona-live-amsterdam-orchestrator/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 09:27:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/speaking-at-percona-live-amsterdam-orchestrator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a week&#39;s time I&#39;ll be speaking at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/europe-amsterdam-2015/&#34;&gt;Percona Live Amsterdam&lt;/a&gt;. I will be presenting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/europe-amsterdam-2015/sessions/managing-and-visualizing-your-replication-topologies-orchestrator&#34;&gt;Managing and Visualizing your replication topologies with Orchestrator&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;23 September 4:20PM&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/europe-amsterdam-2015/sessions/managing-and-visualizing-your-replication-topologies-orchestrator&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk will present &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/outbrain/orchestrator&#34;&gt;orchestrator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, on which I&#39;ve been working for the last year and a half, originally at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.outbrain.com&#34;&gt;Outbrain&lt;/a&gt; and now at &lt;a href=&#34;https://workingatbooking.com/&#34;&gt;Booking.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will show off what &lt;em&gt;orchestrator&lt;/em&gt; can do to manage your replication topologies. From visualization, through topology refactoring to automated crash recoveries, &lt;em&gt;orchestrator&lt;/em&gt; today plays a key role at Booking.com infrastructure, at scale (oh I love using these words).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can expect an outrageous demo, a visual walkthrough, some command line examples, and a lot on the logic and mechanisms behind &lt;em&gt;orchestrator&lt;/em&gt;. I will present the difficult problems &lt;em&gt;orchestrator&lt;/em&gt; covers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;orchestrator&lt;/em&gt; is free and open source, and is built to be as generic as possible; it is known to be used by multiple well known companies these days, so please join the party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that, I conclude with the almighty motto:&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/keep-calm-and-let-orchestrator-handle-it-transp-m.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-7399 alignnone&#34; src=&#34;/blog/blog/assets/keep-calm-and-let-orchestrator-handle-it-transp-m.png&#34; alt=&#34;keep-calm-and-let-orchestrator-handle-it-transp-m&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;571&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://speakerdeck.com/shlominoach/managing-and-visualizing-your-replication-topologies-with-orchestrator&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live Amsterdam: Community Dinner, Sep. 22nd</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/percona-live-amsterdam-community-dinner-sep-22nd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2015 19:21:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/percona-live-amsterdam-community-dinner-sep-22nd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Keeping up with tradition, there will be a community event held at the upcoming &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/europe-amsterdam-2015/&#34;&gt;Percona Live Europe: Amsterdam 2015&lt;/a&gt; conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.booking.com&#34;&gt;Booking.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; will be hosting the event at the company&#39;s headquarters in the heart of Amsterdam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will hold a community dinner (dish selection, includes vegetarian; beverages will be served) in our caffeteria and hope to add some spicy activities to the event!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Space is limited, and tickets can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/community-dinner-bookingcom-tickets-17901675393&#34;&gt;purchased via Eventbrite&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Daniël van Eeden and Jean-François Gagné for their work in making this happen!&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Tuesday, September 22, 2015 from 6:30 PM to 10:00 PM (CEST)&lt;br /&gt;
Herengracht 597, 1017 CE&lt;br /&gt;
Amsterdam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Location: &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/06oOA&#34;&gt;https://goo.gl/maps/06oOA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walking route from conference venue: &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/Ocptu&#34;&gt;https://goo.gl/maps/Ocptu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe style=&#34;border: 0;&#34; src=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m28!1m12!1m3!1d9743.703328920092!2d4.896253511753787!3d52.37176484148813!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!4m13!3e2!4m5!1s0x47c609af134a69db%3A0xa010dcc86a7b3f04!2sM%C3%B6venpick+Hotel+Amsterdam+City+Centre%2C+Piet+Heinkade%2C+Amsterdam!3m2!1d52.3778973!2d4.9142855999999995!4m5!1s0x47c609959752b349%3A0x7d8516d374ac50cd!2sBooking.com%2C+Herengracht+597%2C+1017+CE+Amsterdam!3m2!1d52.3656116!2d4.8984594!5e0!3m2!1sen!2snl!4v1439486186201&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;450&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live 2015: Reflections</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/percona-live-2015-reflections/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2015 03:41:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/percona-live-2015-reflections/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some personal reflections on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2015/&#34;&gt;PerconaLive 2015&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Percona acquires Tokutek&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well done! Tokutek develops the TokuDB storage engine for MySQL and TokuMX engine for MongoDB. I will discuss the MySQL aspect only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TokuDB was released as open source in 2013. It has attained a lot of traction and I have used it myself for some time. I met issues with locking or otherwise operational difficulties which I reported, and otherwise was fascinated by such features as great compression, online schema changes, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently another company, InfiniDB, that also released its MySQL-backed codebase as open source, went out of business. I was afraid the same might happen to Tokutek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see Percona&#39;s purchase as a very good move for the community. I saw a lot of TokuDB interest in Percona for some time now, and it is clearly interested in the technology. I expect they will add their own hands-on experience into the development of more operations-friendly features; put effort in solving locking issues (it&#39;s been a while since I last checked, of course some of these may have been addressed by now). I am guessing they will work on a Galera/TokuDB integration and offer a &#34;Toku-XtraDB-Cluster&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TokuDB can compete with InnoDB in many places, while in others each will have its distinct advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see this is as good news for the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Awards and Lightning Talks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a completely different subject, I believe it is commonly accepted that this year&#39;s setup for the community awards &amp;amp; lightning talks was unsuccessful. The noise was astounding, human traffic was interrupting and overall this was a poor experience. We (Giuseppe Maxia, Kortney Runyan &amp;amp; myself) made a quick, informal brainstorming on this and came up with a couple ideas. One of which we hope to try in the upcoming &lt;em&gt;Percona Live Europe - Amsterdam&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We apologize to the speakers for the difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Percona Live Europe - Amsterdam&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haha! Having recently relocated to the Netherlands I&#39;m of course very happy. But regardless, Percona Live London was fun - and yet running on low fuel. I think it was a great idea to change location (and more locations expected in the future). This is the path taken by such conferences as OSCon, Velocity, Strata and more. Amsterdam in particular, as I&#39;ve recently learned, is especially appreciated by many. I think this conf will do great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Woz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now for something completely different. Woz&#39; talk was that. I&#39;m happy he came; I appreciate that he discussed education; and it was fun.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at Percona Live: Pseudo GTID and Easy Replication Topology Management</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/speaking-at-percona-live-pseudo-gtid-and-easy-replication-topology-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2015 17:42:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/speaking-at-percona-live-pseudo-gtid-and-easy-replication-topology-management/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In two weeks time I will be presenting &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2015/sessions/pseudo-gtid-and-easy-replication-management&#34;&gt;Pseudo GTID and Easy Replication Topology Management&lt;/a&gt; at Percona Live. From the time I submitted the proposal a LOT has been developed, experimented, deployed and used with both &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/mysql/refactoring-replication-topology-with-pseudo-gtid&#34;&gt;Pseudo GTID&lt;/a&gt; and with &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/outbrain/orchestrator&#34;&gt;orchestrator&lt;/a&gt;. In my talk I will:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suggest that you skip the &#34;to GTID or not to GTID&#34; question and go for the lightweight Pseudo GTID&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show how Pseudo GTID is used in production to recover from various replication failures and server crashes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do an outrageous demonstration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tell you about 50,000 successful experiments and tests done in production&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show off orchestrator and its support for Pseudo GTID, including automated crash analysis and recovery mechanism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will further show how the orchestrator tooling makes for a less restrictive, more performant, less locking, non-intrusive, trusted and lightweight replication topology management solution.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/orchestrator-topology-simple.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;wp-image-7206 size-full&#34; src=&#34;/blog/blog/assets/orchestrator-topology-simple.png&#34; alt=&#34;orchestrator-topology-simple&#34; width=&#34;1010&#34; height=&#34;286&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; An anonymized topology&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please come by my talk! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[speakerdeck https://speakerdeck.com/shlominoach/pseudo-gtid-and-easy-mysql-replication-topology-management]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live 2015: Call for Papers is open</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/percona-live-2015-call-for-papers-is-open/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 08:25:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/percona-live-2015-call-for-papers-is-open/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;And not for long!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Call for Papers for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2015&#34;&gt;Percona Live MySQL Conference and Expo&lt;/a&gt;, to be held at Santa Clara in April 2015, is open. The dead line for submissions is &lt;strong&gt;Nov. 16th&lt;/strong&gt;; that&#39;s just around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with previous years, we will hold a &lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt; day conference, the first being a tutorials day and three days for sessions, BoF and lightning talks, as well as community events. The committee is expecting to review at about 250-300 submissions, out of which it will pick at about 100 talks to schedule or reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be using these tracks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Availability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DevOps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance Optimization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replication and Backup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MySQL in the Cloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MySQL and NoSQL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MySQL Case Studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What’s New in MySQL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year we will roughly pre-define the desired number of sessions we wish to have per track. This is not set in stone and everything is fluid. Yet, this will give us better guidelines at choosing and pursuing content for this conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Submitting a proposal&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We encourage all members of the community to submit their tutorial/session/BoF proposals as soon as possible. Please register/login at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2015/&#34;&gt;conference home page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guidelines for submitting a proposal are generally unchanged; please review past recommendations: &lt;a href=&#34;http://datacharmer.blogspot.com/2008/09/how-to-get-your-proposal-accepted-to.html&#34;&gt;[1],&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/12/19/how-to-write-a-good-mysql-conference-proposal/&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/mysql/percona-live-mysql-conference-and-expo-2012-a-note-on-proposals&#34;&gt;[3], &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/mysql/percona-live-mysql-conference-expo-2014-call-for-papers-guidelines&#34;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. To add to all these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do note that we are likely to only review a proposal just once. Please submit only after you have finalized your draft.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a reasonable length of proposal. We believe 250 - 300 words are quite enough for a good proposal. Please don&#39;t write an essay, and remember that you proposal is what gets printed on the schedule, and what is read by the conference attendees when choosing the next talk to go to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a descent Bio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The committee&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year&#39;s committee includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calvin Sun (Twitter)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Schneider (Groupon)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colin Charles (MariaDB)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gwen Shapira (Cloudera)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harrison Fisk (Facebook)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jay Janssen (Percona)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jeremy Cole (Google)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John Scott (Wellcentive)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Morgan Tocker (Oracle)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patrick Gilbraith (HP)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peter Zaitsev (Percona)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sean Chighizola (Big Fish)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shivinder Singh (Verizon Wireless)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tamar Bercovici (Box)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;myself, Shlomi Noach (Conference Chairman)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to reviewing your papers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some anecdotes I learned at Percona Live</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/some-anecdotes-i-learned-at-percona-live/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2014 04:06:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/some-anecdotes-i-learned-at-percona-live/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While on the plane back home I wrote down all my impressions from Percona Live 2014. Have lots of TODOs and great ideas to implement. Among all my impressions, there were a few anecdotes worth noting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5.6 GTID is still unfriendly. It will require complete shutdown &amp;amp; reconfiguration of your entire replication topology; and some companies present hacks around this. Notable, Facebook recoded GTID related code (slave agrees to replicate with GTID even though its master still uses binlog coordinates). Booking.com have their own hack around slowly migrating their topologies. And in a great lightning talk we were shown how to patch MySQL such that the relay logs turn into a  consistent GTID-like coordinate system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Galera replication has been implemented for TokuDB (only active-passive mode, not active-active). This came as a surprise to Tokutek ; apparently Codership did this within a few hours of work. The rest is up for Tokutek!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WebScaleSQL is a cool initiative that aims to assist in pushing commonly desired featured back upstream. It is Web Scale. It is also not a productio0n distribution and I do not expect it to be, It is not a fork that is meant for the common DBA to download and deploy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tungsten replicator has MySQL to Hadoop replication using staging tables - an auditing of changes that are group-deployed on Hadoop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Still so many people unfamiliar with MySQLSandbox. It&#39;s such a basic tool, especially for testing and local installations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Still misconceptions about common_schema. Yes, I do use it on production.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everyone has the same problems :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replication is still queen of MySQL&#39;s featureset. We&#39;re still all about failing over, promoting, scaling via replication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linux rules. Where two MacBooks failed to connect to the projector, my Lenovo/Ubuntu Linux did the job just fine and saved the day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at Percona Live: common_schema, MySQL DevOps</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/speaking-at-perconalive-common_schema-mysql-devops/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2014 10:27:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/speaking-at-perconalive-common_schema-mysql-devops/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In less than a month I&#39;ll be giving these two talks at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/&#34;&gt;Percona Live&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/sessions/commonschema-dbas-framework-mysql&#34;&gt;common_schema: DBA&#39;s framework for MySQL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are still unfamiliar with &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.google.com/p/common-schema/&#34;&gt;common_schema,&lt;/a&gt; this will make for a good introduction. I&#39;ll give you multiple reasons why you would want to use it, and how it would come to &lt;em&gt;immediate&lt;/em&gt; use at your company. I do mean &lt;em&gt;immediate&lt;/em&gt;, as in previous &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; presentations I happened to get feedback emails from attendees within the same or next day letting me know how &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; solved an insistent problem of theirs or how it exposed an unknown status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll review some useful views &amp;amp; routines, and discuss the ease and power of QueryScript. &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; is a Swiss-knife of solutions, and all from within your MySQL server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am using &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; in production on a regular basis, and it happened to be hero of the day in multiple occasions. I&#39;ll present a couple such cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/shlominoach/commonschema-22-dbas-framework-for-mysql&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/sessions/mysql-devops-outbrain&#34;&gt;MySQL DevOps @ Outbrain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a technical talk touching at some cultural issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.outbrain.com/about/what-is-outbrain&#34;&gt;Outbrain&lt;/a&gt;, where I work, we have two blessings: a large group of engineers and a large dataset. We at the infrastructure team, together with the ops team, are responsible for the availability of the data. What we really like is technology which lets the owners of a problem be able to recognize it and take care of it. We want ops guys to do ops, and engineers to do engineering. And we want them to be able to talk to each other and &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What tools can you use to increase visibility? To allow sharing of data between the teams? I&#39;ll share some tools and techniques that allow us to automate deployments, detect a malfunctioning/abusing service, deploy schema changes across dozens of hosts, control data retention, monitor connections, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We like open source. The tools discussed are mostly open source, or open sourced by Outbrain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll explain why these tools matter, and how they serve the purpose of removing friction between teams, allowing for quick analysis of problems and overall visibility on all things that happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/shlominoach/mysql-devops-at-outbrain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Do come by!&lt;/h4&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live - call for &#34;Hall of Shame&#34; talks</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/percona-live-call-for-hall-of-shame-talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Mar 2014 15:02:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/percona-live-call-for-hall-of-shame-talks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ve got some spare time on Percona Live during the lightning talks session, and are spontaneously calling for &#34;Hall of Shame&#34; submissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What is this about?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We just had a wonderful &lt;a href=&#34;http://summit2014.reversim.com/agenda&#34;&gt;Reversim Summit&lt;/a&gt; a couple weeks back, where we held the &#34;Hall of Shame&#34; session. We are used to hear talks about success stories and great new technologies. Well, this session is your chance to come up and say: &#34;I messed up, and I&#39;m proud of it!&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will have 3-4 minutes to tell us about how you once accidentally dropped your database; corrupted your data; brought your company&#39;s service down. The greater the damage, the greater the appeal! But we&#39;re looking for the funny edge - not for a tragedy. There are no slides. Just a &#34;Hall of Shame&#34; screen behind you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The response we got on &lt;em&gt;Reversim Summit&lt;/em&gt;? It was amazing. The audience was literally in tears; there were such hilarious stories that we could hardly keep up. People were spontaneously offering their stories and the organizers had to hold them back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be telling about your mess up - so please make sure you feel OK about this. For what it&#39;s worth, I will contribute my own shameful, shameful story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this is new &amp;amp; experimental for the Percona Live conference, and we don&#39;t have many slots. If no one submits - that&#39;s OK. If too many submit, we&#39;ll have to cut most. As conferences go, we may end up with a last moment open timeslot, so if you&#39;re spontaneous that could be your chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Ready to submit?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please send an email to &lt;a&gt;mysql.hall&lt;wbr&gt;&lt;/wbr&gt;ofshame&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;@&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;gmail.com&lt;wbr&gt;&lt;/wbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with a brief description of what you want to share. I&#39;ll be reviewing these submissions and either approve, reject or hold you on a waiting list. I assume this will go by First Come First Served. The deadline for submissions is &lt;strong&gt;Friday, Mar 14th&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Community Awards 2014: Call for Nominations!</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/mysql-community-awards-2014-call-for-nominations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 08:00:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/mysql-community-awards-2014-call-for-nominations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;2014&lt;/strong&gt; MySQL Community Awards event will take place, as usual, in Santa Clara, April 2014, during the Percona Live MySQL Conference &amp;amp; Expo (currently scheduled at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/program/schedule/sessions-day-2&#34;&gt;Thursday, April 3rd 2014&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MySQL Community Awards is a community based initiative. The idea is to publicly recognize contributors to the MySQL ecosystem. The entire process of discussing, voting and awarding is controlled by an independent group of community members, typically based of past winners or their representatives, as well as known contributors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a self-appointed, self-declared, self-making-up-the-rules-as-it-goes committee. It is also very aware of the importance of the community; a no-nonsense, non-political, adhering to tradition, self criticizing committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Call for Nominations is open. We are seeking the community’s assistance in nominating candidates in the following categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Community Contributor of the year 2014&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a personal award; a winner would a person who has made contribution to the MySQL ecosystem. This could be via development, advocating, blogging, speaking, supporting, etc. All things go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Application of the year 2014&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An application, project, product etc. which supports the MySQL ecosystem by either contributing code, complementing its behaviour, supporting its use, etc. This could range from a one man open source project to a large scale social service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;MySQL Community Awards: Corporate Contributor of the year 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A company who made contribution to the MySQL ecosystem. This might be a corporate which released major open source code; one that advocates for MySQL; one that help out community members by... anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see the criteria are flexible. They all boil down to one thing: what gain the nominees provide the community with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please also see the &lt;a href=&#34;http://openlife.cc/blogs/2013/january/call-nominations-mysql-community-awards-2013&#34;&gt;2013 Call for Nominations&lt;/a&gt; by Henrik Ingo for more insights; also note the &lt;a href=&#34;http://openlife.cc/blogs/2012/february/mysql-hall-fame&#34;&gt;MySQL Hall of Fame&lt;/a&gt; (up to 2012) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://openlife.cc/blogs/2013/april/mysql-community-awards-2013-and-winners-are&#34;&gt;2013 winners&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Process of nomination and voting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone can nominate anyone. When nominating, please make sure to provide a brief explanation on why the candidate is eligible to get the award. Make a good case!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee will review all nominations and vote; it typically takes two rounds of votes to pick the winners, and a lot of discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be &lt;em&gt;up to&lt;/em&gt; three winners in each category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods of nomination:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send en email to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mysql.community.awards&lt;/strong&gt;@&lt;strong&gt;gmail.com&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comment to this post&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assuming you can provide a reasonable description in &lt;strong&gt;140&lt;/strong&gt; characters, tweet your nomination at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=MySQLAwards&amp;amp;src=typd&amp;amp;f=realtime&#34;&gt;#MySQLAwards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please submit your nominations no later than &lt;strong&gt;Sunday, &lt;del&gt;January&lt;/del&gt; February 23, 2014&lt;/strong&gt;. (whoops)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The committee&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Callaghan and myself (Shlomi Noach) are acting as co-secretaries; we will be non-voting (except for breaking ties). Members are: Baron Schwartz, Domas Mituzas, Gerry Narvaja, Giuseppe Maxia, Jeremy Cole, Justin Swanhart, Marc Delisle, Mark Leith, Ronald Bradford, Sarah Novotny, Sheeri K. Cabral, Tim Callaghan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee communicates throughout the nomination and voting process to exchange views and opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The awards&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awards are traditionally (as in this year) donated by some party, who&#39;s identity remains secret.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Support&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a community effort; we ask for your support in spreading the word and of course in nominating candidates. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live 2014 schedule released; BoF and Lightning Talks Call for Papers continues</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/percona-live-2014-schedule-released-bof-and-lightning-talks-call-for-papers-continues/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 11:01:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/percona-live-2014-schedule-released-bof-and-lightning-talks-call-for-papers-continues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The complete tutorial &amp;amp; session schedule for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/&#34;&gt;Percona Live MySQL Conference &amp;amp; Expo 2014&lt;/a&gt; is released. This schedule offers both a sense of achievement as well as a sense of regret; for I believe the schedule is very good, and yet some good proposals had to be left out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an inevitable result of a conference that is popular and receives far more proposals than can fit within the time frames. This conference offers &lt;strong&gt;96&lt;/strong&gt; session slots and &lt;strong&gt;16&lt;/strong&gt; 3-hour tutorial slots. We got well over &lt;strong&gt;300&lt;/strong&gt; proposals -- I&#39;m not even sure how to count them -- and they just can&#39;t all fit in. My sincere apologies to all those left out. A proposal of mine was just rejected yesterday from another conference; I can sympathize and empathize with all turned down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of our interest in having a diversity of talks and speakers, we have promoted talks by less frequent speakers and newly presenting companies. We are happy to grow the community!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although titled &#34;Percona Live&#34;, this conference&#39;s program is managed by a diverse and independent committee. We had good discussions and some very good thinking and advice were offered. I&#39;m happy to acknowledge and thank the committee members:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cédric Peintre, Dailymotion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giuseppe Maxia, Continuent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ivan Zoratti, SkySQL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jay Janssen, Percona&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jeremy Cole, Google&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laine Campbell, PalominoDB (now Blackbird, congrats!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liz van Dijk, Percona&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roland Bouman, Pentaho&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tim Callaghan, Tokutek&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Todd Farmer, Oracle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;myself, Outbrain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the schedule I&#39;m as always eager to attend many more sessions than I can; until I get more replicas of myself, It&#39;s again down to choosing between multiple prominent talks at each time slot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to all those who submitted a proposal! (It&#39;s cool, just saying)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Birds of a Feather, Lightning Talks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Call for papers continues! You are encouraged to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/user&#34;&gt;submit your proposals&lt;/a&gt; until end of January. These proposals are reviewed by the committee, and eventually chosen and scheduled by Giuseppe Maxia. See also:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://datacharmer.blogspot.co.il/2013/11/call-for-papers-with-lightning-talks.html&#34;&gt;Call for papers (with lightning talks): Percona Live MySQL Conference 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://datacharmer.blogspot.co.il/2013/12/submissions-at-percona-live-santa-clara.html&#34;&gt;Submissions at Percona Live Santa Clara 2014 and Lightning talks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why a professional conference must have a committee, and what that committee does</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/why-a-professional-conference-must-have-a-committee-and-what-that-committee-does/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 11:11:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/why-a-professional-conference-must-have-a-committee-and-what-that-committee-does/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What exactly is it that a conference committee does? This post comes as response to a comment on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mysqlperformanceblog.com/2013/12/11/percona-live-2014-conference-sneak-peek/&#34;&gt;A sneak peek at the Percona Live MySQL Conference &amp;amp; Expo 2014&lt;/a&gt;, reading:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Why the same committee each year? Community should vote on proposals and committee should just work schedule,etc.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll pick the glove and shed some light into the work of the committee. While this specific comment related to the Percona Live conference, I trust that my opinions expressed below apply just as well to any (technical?) professional conference; the point below can equally apply to conferences from Oracle MySQL Connect, O&#39;Reilly Velocity to FOSDEM &amp;amp; PyCon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can sum up the entire answer with one word: &#34;Discussion&#34;. For a breakdown, please read through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;First, what&#39;s not feasible with community-based voting, and what looks very wrong&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why not open up a voting system and let the community do the rating? I always disliked the &#34;send an SMS to this number to vote for X&#34; approach. It is so unbalanced and unreliable: if I were to submit a proposal describing how my company invented/develops/uses X to do great things, I can expect my co-workers to vote for me. In fact, my company would possibly ask my co-workers to do so. I stand a better chance if I work in a large company; less so in a small company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anonymous votes tend to be touched by politics. I could vote for my company, against a competing product, for my friends, against people I dislike, and none the wiser. We can take away anonymity, which means my votes will be public, which means they are visible to all. In which case my ranking will be affected by what people I rate would think of me; which means my rating would not be based on strictly professional/technical grounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before we drop into this endless pit, let&#39;s consider: will I, as a KMyPyVelocirails community member, really engage in reviewing over 300 submissions? How many members of my community would take so many hours of their time to do so? Let me clarify, this is a part-time job. It requires time, and it requires a mindset. I&#39;m guessing here that you cannot count on everyone rating all talks. Some more prominent talks will be reviewed by more people, others may be left little to not reviewed in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of a purely community based rating is romantic and beautiful, but not feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there&#39;s the &lt;em&gt;discussion&lt;/em&gt;. Let&#39;s look at some of the things the committee is engaged in to clarify.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Duties, responsibility and actions of a conference committee&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following discussion cannot be an exhaustive description of a committee&#39;s work, but it can give a good glimpse into its scope. We begin with the commitment the members take upon themselves: to invest their time and will in the committee&#39;s duties. Once you join in, you are expected to work and deliver.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The duties of the reviewing committee extend beyond reviewing the proposals -- though this duty is the most critical of all, as it serves the basis for all others. So let&#39;s describe this first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Reviewing the proposals&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reviewing papers is more than rating them (1-5 stars). We also comment and share our opinion. Members typically explain why they rated the way they did, especially on low rating. Our ratings and comments are visible to other members, and they can react on these. For example, I can disagree with one&#39;s comments and counter-comment myself. We can continue this discussion in our mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might throw in our experience in attending the same talk in the past. Was it good? Was it bad? Yes, it matters; we want the conference to be successful, and our personal experience is something we bring to the table. We might have some inside knowledge about an emerging technology, or speakers may share with us such knowledge in private section (&lt;em&gt;&#34;By the time this talk is given, this project will have been released as open source&#34;&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may suggest improvements: &lt;em&gt;&#34;Better make this tutorial 3 hours instead of 6&#34;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&#34;Should include this topic as well&#34;&lt;/em&gt;. We might (and sometimes do) approach speakers to refine their submissions if we think they can make for good sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can express our true professional opinion on proposals. We wouldn&#39;t always want to share in public; this private discussion works for the benefit of all - there is no reason to suspect we use fluttery nor insults. We just say what we think within our small group -- and still be prepared for backfire from our peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, wait. By which guidelines do we vote? Before we even start rating, we set the very basic guidelines, such as &#34;what content are we looking for; what&#39;s this conference about, what it is not, what are the rules for rating, ...&#34;. Can I rate talks submitted by my colleagues? Would that be unfair? But if so, am I allowed to rate our competitors? Wouldn&#39;t &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; be unfair as well? Is there an end to it? We set these rules up front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Meta&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the reviewing process we collect meta-data about the submitted papers. Do we find content that is missing? Do we have enough &#34;beginner&#34; talks?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some speakers submit 5-6 talks, in the hope than one or two make it through. But they don&#39;t really intend to submit 5 or 6 talks if all happen to get approved. And the committee also prefers a variety of speakers. The committee (or committee chairman) reaches to those speakers to understand better their limitations. We can therefore reject talks based on high submission number per speaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We typically very quickly stumble upon the issue of overlapping content. Some topics are proposed again and again by multiple speakers. We take notes and balance the figures. We sometimes reject talks not because the abstracts are bad, but because we have so many other competing talks on same topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may choose to promote an open source product. We may be passionate about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we do reach a conclusion that some content is missing, we may pursue the issue by contacting speakers or potential speakers to submit papers on the subject. We may contact specific companies or speakers that we know would provide good value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We make backup plans: speakers cancel; some don&#39;t get Visas, some fall ill. We make a &#34;Waitlist&#34; of sessions and verify with speakers that they would be able to provide them upon request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speakers may have personal limitations, e.g. only being able to attend on this and that days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Non reviewing tasks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are further engaged in shaping the general shape of the conference. The organizers consult with us on various topics. I guess this really depends on the nature of the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see from all the above, this is far from just rating all the talks and picking the &#34;top &lt;strong&gt;100&lt;/strong&gt; talks&#34;. There are a lot of constraints, limitations, contradictions, and issues to go through. This cannot be an automated &#34;community vote&#34; thing. And the moment you put someone at the position of making decision, you&#39;re effectively reinventing the committee.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live: MySQL Conference &amp; Expo 2014: call for papers &amp; guidelines</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/percona-live-mysql-conference-expo-2014-call-for-papers-guidelines/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2013 11:59:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/percona-live-mysql-conference-expo-2014-call-for-papers-guidelines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Call for papers for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/&#34;&gt;Percona Live MySQL Conference &amp;amp; Expo 2014&lt;/a&gt; is open. As in previous year, I have the honour of being conference committee chairman, which means I&#39;m in particular part of the reviewing committee. I wish to add to &lt;a href=&#34;http://datacharmer.blogspot.co.il/2013/11/call-for-papers-with-lightning-talks.html&#34;&gt;Giuseppe&#39;s fine observations and suggestions&lt;/a&gt;. On submitting a talk, please consider the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make it right the first time (an old advice by Baron). We will not be able to review your proposal more than once. We will not be iterating the proposals again and again to see what&#39;s changed, nor will we have a feed for updated content. We will not be able to diff any changes you made to your proposal. Get it right the first time, this is the one time we will read your proposal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &lt;em&gt;rare occasions&lt;/em&gt; we may think your proposal is just too important to be thrown just for bad description/grammar/language, and we may contact you to refine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The proposal must be as clear to us as for your target audience. Good proposals are easy to understand. Make it clear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being super-famous does not grant you immediate approval. It helps if you&#39;ve given the talk &lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt; times in the past, and we&#39;ve all seen it and it was widely acknowledged as one of the best talks ever. But then again, if that&#39;s the kind of speaker you are, you probably know how to write a good proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee seeks the audience&#39;s best interest. We assume the audience&#39;s common sense is similar, via extrapolation, to our own. We therefore assume that if we think a proposal is bad, so will the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&#39;re a commercial vendor and you want to make a proposal, that&#39;s fine.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I suppose the best way would be through the sponsor program&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But otherwise we actually accept talks on commercial/closed source solutions. Be advised, however, that the committee members will typically wish to promote open source &amp;amp; free solutions, and so commercial/closed source talks are at some disadvantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are owner/employee of commercial/closed source solution, and you&#39;re going to speak on a subject that is related to your product, please be very explicit:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;either note (in private notes, if you like) that you will be, say, comparing your own product along with other products, and provide full disclosure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;or let us know you will in fact &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; speak about your own product, and make us sigh in relief.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In short, don&#39;t let us suspect this is going to be a sales pitch in disguise. It is one of the quickest ways to get your proposal rejected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be interested to learn that last year, a proposal made by an influential and a well known speaker was turned down for that exact reason. Even if he had no intention of doing a sales pitch, that&#39;s what it looked like to us, and by extrapolation to the audience.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also ask you that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery is loyal to your proposal. If you suggest you&#39;re going to speak about &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt;, then people may choose to arrive at your room and miss other talks because they would like to hear about &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt;. Please respect your audience and deliver &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt;, not &lt;strong&gt;Y&lt;/strong&gt; (this is based on real event). Of course we appreciate that by the time your talk is delivered the landscape changes a little so adjustments are fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Please make sure your talk fits within the designated timeframe (typically &lt;strong&gt;50&lt;/strong&gt; minute for sessions), and respect your audience by allowing them to get to their next talk, and respect the next speaker by allowing him to prepare and begin in time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, do not be discouraged should your talk not be approved. There are many reasons like overlapping content, starvation of certain tracks; but the honest truth is that we simply cannot accept all talks. Last year we got about &lt;strong&gt;250&lt;/strong&gt; submissions for &lt;strong&gt;96&lt;/strong&gt; slots (give or take). This is good, since we can pick what we believe is the winning combination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the above based on our work on the &lt;strong&gt;2013&lt;/strong&gt; conference. Sounds too complex? This is just a breakdown of what we think is common sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Submit a proposal today!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>common_schema: speaking at Percona Live London, Nov. 2013</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/common_schema-speaking-at-percona-live-london-nov-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 17:30:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/common_schema-speaking-at-percona-live-london-nov-2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In one week&#39;s time I&#39;ll be presenting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/london-2013/sessions/commonschema-dbas-framework-mysql&#34;&gt;common_schema: DBA&#39;s framework for MySQL&lt;/a&gt; at Percona Live, London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk introduces the rich toolset known as &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.google.com/p/common-schema/&#34;&gt;common_schema&lt;/a&gt;. It is free, open source, extremely useful in solving DBA &amp;amp; developer tasks, and is the next best thing ever invented next to SQL pie charts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll introduce:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Views, with which you can detect and terminate idle transactions, blocking transactions; roll your range partitions; find duplicate keys; block/unblock accounts; get fine grained privileges per account; find AUTO_ICNREMENT free space; ...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Routines: do meta executions such as eval(); get query checksums; duplicating accounts; killing suspicious connections; security auditing; parsing JSON data; ...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QueryScript: if you&#39;re not using it, you&#39;re missing on a powerful scripting language tightly integrated with SQL/MySQL. We&#39;ll see the basic constructs, variables, loops; the more sophisticated MySQL/locks/overhead/danger aware constructs such as foreach &amp;amp; split; throttling, exceptions, it&#39;s all in there. I&#39;ll present real scripts that saved the day and challenge you to implement them in another scripting language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Briefly introducing rdebug: stored routine debugger and debugging API&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roadmap (some cool things coming along)&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What this talk isn&#39;t&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A tedious &#34;read the manual aloud&#34;. Nor is it a comprehensive listing of all functionality. These would be the surest way of sending you to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What this talk is&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A view into the concepts behind &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt;; the reasons this project has justification to exist; the various problems it solves; and yes, interesting examples. Every single &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; feature was developed out of real world need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am confident you&#39;ll find &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; to have something you need that will improve your work as a developer or a DBA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk is similar to &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/mysql/speaking-at-percona-live-2013-common_schema-lightning-talks&#34;&gt;the one I gave&lt;/a&gt; at Santa Clara this April. It is updated with new content following recent developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/shlominoach/commonschema-22&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live 2013 keynotes: followup questions and discussion</title>
      <link>/blog/mysql/percona-live-2013-keynotes-followup-questions-and-discussion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 07:23:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mysql/percona-live-2013-keynotes-followup-questions-and-discussion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are a few questions remained open for me from Percona Live 2013 about things that have been said during keynotes; I will appreciate a discussion on comments. Here goes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Question #1&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2013/sessions/keynote-panel-impact-mysql-56-and-its-future-x&#34;&gt;Brian Aker (HP) asks Simone Brunozzi (Amazon)&lt;/a&gt; what the underlying technology for DynamoDB is. Simone says can&#39;t disclose. Brian says: &#34;it&#39;s MySQL!!&#34;. Simone says: &#34;can&#39;t disclose&#34;. Brian insists: &#34;it&#39;s MySQL!!&#34;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously? I will be very much surprised to learn that DynamoDB uses MySQL; it doesn&#39;t make sense to me. Why would Brian Aker say that though? Did he just mean to tease Simone or is there something I just don&#39;t get?&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Yes, Brian?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Question #2&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2013/sessions/keynote-state-mysql-ecosystem&#34;&gt;Matt Aslett speaks about adoption of MySQL &amp;amp; variants&lt;/a&gt;, and expected adoption in next years, Mentions MariaDB, Percona Server, SkySQL. KEeps saying how the SkySQL server gets more traction.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does he mean? There&#39;s no SkySQL fork; does he mean SkySQL cloud offer? Or just SkySQL support services, typically for MariaDB variant? But in that case, SkySQL is out of context. What&#39;s going on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Question #3&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Matt Aslett presents quite pessimistic prediction for MySQL. Reduced popularity in next years. Relatively good news for MontyProgram/MariaDB; otherwise a lot of switch-off to PostgreSQL, poor adoption for Continuent, low ratios of &#34;evaluation&#34; to &#34;adoption&#34; of technologies; really quite depressing. Later mentions at about &lt;strong&gt;200+&lt;/strong&gt; questionnaires.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t have a special interest here as I don&#39;t work for any mentioned company; other than my general desire to see the ecosystem flourishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are &lt;strong&gt;200+&lt;/strong&gt; people enough to both give a faithful picture of current MySQL usage and adoption? Are they enough for prediction &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt; year into the future? &lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt; years into the future?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Israel, with less than &lt;strong&gt;8M&lt;/strong&gt; population, election surveys usually look at &lt;strong&gt;500+&lt;/strong&gt; people. To me it doesn&#39;t sound a lot, but statistics is not my strong skill. However those picked for the survey have to be a diverse population, distributed in similar ratio to overall population (so Jews, Muslims, Christians, Orthodox, income level, geographic location, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does the same happen with those &lt;strong&gt;200+&lt;/strong&gt; questionnaires in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://451research.com/&#34;&gt;451 research&lt;/a&gt;? The reason I ask is this: at the end of keynote Matt says: &#34;if you want your voice to be heard, if you think differently, contact me, and I&#39;ll add you to our survey&#34;. Does this mean anyone stepping up is included? Great, so a hypothetical company called GalleriaDB would encourage its 50 employees to enlist, thereby completely shifting the balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who are those &lt;strong&gt;200+&lt;/strong&gt; people in the survey? World wide known experts? Your regular DBA? Your remote DBA consultant? Your web developer? Do they represent the overall MySQL ecosystem population? Do their insights into the future collide with those of everyone?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Please discuss below&lt;/h4&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>