<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Speaking on code.openark.org</title>
    <link>/blog/tags/speaking/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Speaking on code.openark.org</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2015 21:06:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/blog/tags/speaking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at FOSDEM: Pseudo GTID and easy replication management</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/01/29/speaking-at-fosdem-pseudo-gtid-and-easy-replication-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2015 21:06:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/01/29/speaking-at-fosdem-pseudo-gtid-and-easy-replication-management/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This coming Sunday I&#39;ll be presenting &lt;a href=&#34;https://fosdem.org/2015/schedule/event/pseudo_gtid/&#34;&gt;Pseudo GTID and easy replication management&lt;/a&gt; at FOSDEM, Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s been a lot of development on &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/mysql/refactoring-replication-topology-with-pseudo-gtid&#34;&gt;Pseudo GTID&lt;/a&gt; these last few weeks. In this talk I&#39;ll show you how you can use Pseudo GTID instead of &#34;normal&#34; GTID to easily repoint your slaves, recover from intermediate master failure, promote slaves to masters as well as emply crash safe replication without crash safe replication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, I will show how you can achieve all the above with &lt;em&gt;less constraints&lt;/em&gt; than GTID, and for bulk operations -- with &lt;em&gt;less overhead&lt;/em&gt; and in &lt;em&gt;shorter time&lt;/em&gt;. You will also see that Pseudo GTID is a non intrusive solution which does not require you to change anything in your topologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moral: I&#39;ll try and convince you to &lt;em&gt;drop your plans for using GTID&lt;/em&gt; in favor of &lt;em&gt;Pseudo GTID&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be employing Pseudo GTID as the basis for high availability and failover at Booking.com on many topologies, and as a safety mechanism in other topologies where we will employ &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.booking.com/mysql_slave_scaling_and_more.html&#34;&gt;Binlog servers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/shlominoach/pseudo-gtid-easy-replication-topology-management-fosdem&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live 2015: Call for Papers is open</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/10/31/percona-live-2015-call-for-papers-is-open/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 08:25:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/10/31/percona-live-2015-call-for-papers-is-open/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;And not for long!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Call for Papers for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2015&#34;&gt;Percona Live MySQL Conference and Expo&lt;/a&gt;, to be held at Santa Clara in April 2015, is open. The dead line for submissions is &lt;strong&gt;Nov. 16th&lt;/strong&gt;; that&#39;s just around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with previous years, we will hold a &lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt; day conference, the first being a tutorials day and three days for sessions, BoF and lightning talks, as well as community events. The committee is expecting to review at about 250-300 submissions, out of which it will pick at about 100 talks to schedule or reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be using these tracks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Availability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DevOps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance Optimization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replication and Backup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MySQL in the Cloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MySQL and NoSQL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MySQL Case Studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What’s New in MySQL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year we will roughly pre-define the desired number of sessions we wish to have per track. This is not set in stone and everything is fluid. Yet, this will give us better guidelines at choosing and pursuing content for this conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Submitting a proposal&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We encourage all members of the community to submit their tutorial/session/BoF proposals as soon as possible. Please register/login at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2015/&#34;&gt;conference home page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guidelines for submitting a proposal are generally unchanged; please review past recommendations: &lt;a href=&#34;http://datacharmer.blogspot.com/2008/09/how-to-get-your-proposal-accepted-to.html&#34;&gt;[1],&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/12/19/how-to-write-a-good-mysql-conference-proposal/&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/mysql/percona-live-mysql-conference-and-expo-2012-a-note-on-proposals&#34;&gt;[3], &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/mysql/percona-live-mysql-conference-expo-2014-call-for-papers-guidelines&#34;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. To add to all these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do note that we are likely to only review a proposal just once. Please submit only after you have finalized your draft.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a reasonable length of proposal. We believe 250 - 300 words are quite enough for a good proposal. Please don&#39;t write an essay, and remember that you proposal is what gets printed on the schedule, and what is read by the conference attendees when choosing the next talk to go to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a descent Bio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The committee&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year&#39;s committee includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calvin Sun (Twitter)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Schneider (Groupon)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colin Charles (MariaDB)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gwen Shapira (Cloudera)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harrison Fisk (Facebook)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jay Janssen (Percona)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jeremy Cole (Google)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John Scott (Wellcentive)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Morgan Tocker (Oracle)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patrick Gilbraith (HP)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peter Zaitsev (Percona)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sean Chighizola (Big Fish)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shivinder Singh (Verizon Wireless)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tamar Bercovici (Box)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;myself, Shlomi Noach (Conference Chairman)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to reviewing your papers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at Percona Live: common_schema, MySQL DevOps</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/03/10/speaking-at-perconalive-common_schema-mysql-devops/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2014 10:27:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/03/10/speaking-at-perconalive-common_schema-mysql-devops/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In less than a month I&#39;ll be giving these two talks at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/&#34;&gt;Percona Live&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/sessions/commonschema-dbas-framework-mysql&#34;&gt;common_schema: DBA&#39;s framework for MySQL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are still unfamiliar with &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.google.com/p/common-schema/&#34;&gt;common_schema,&lt;/a&gt; this will make for a good introduction. I&#39;ll give you multiple reasons why you would want to use it, and how it would come to &lt;em&gt;immediate&lt;/em&gt; use at your company. I do mean &lt;em&gt;immediate&lt;/em&gt;, as in previous &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; presentations I happened to get feedback emails from attendees within the same or next day letting me know how &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; solved an insistent problem of theirs or how it exposed an unknown status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll review some useful views &amp;amp; routines, and discuss the ease and power of QueryScript. &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; is a Swiss-knife of solutions, and all from within your MySQL server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am using &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; in production on a regular basis, and it happened to be hero of the day in multiple occasions. I&#39;ll present a couple such cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/shlominoach/commonschema-22-dbas-framework-for-mysql&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/sessions/mysql-devops-outbrain&#34;&gt;MySQL DevOps @ Outbrain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a technical talk touching at some cultural issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.outbrain.com/about/what-is-outbrain&#34;&gt;Outbrain&lt;/a&gt;, where I work, we have two blessings: a large group of engineers and a large dataset. We at the infrastructure team, together with the ops team, are responsible for the availability of the data. What we really like is technology which lets the owners of a problem be able to recognize it and take care of it. We want ops guys to do ops, and engineers to do engineering. And we want them to be able to talk to each other and &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What tools can you use to increase visibility? To allow sharing of data between the teams? I&#39;ll share some tools and techniques that allow us to automate deployments, detect a malfunctioning/abusing service, deploy schema changes across dozens of hosts, control data retention, monitor connections, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We like open source. The tools discussed are mostly open source, or open sourced by Outbrain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll explain why these tools matter, and how they serve the purpose of removing friction between teams, allowing for quick analysis of problems and overall visibility on all things that happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/shlominoach/mysql-devops-at-outbrain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Do come by!&lt;/h4&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live - call for &#34;Hall of Shame&#34; talks</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/03/08/percona-live-call-for-hall-of-shame-talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Mar 2014 15:02:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/03/08/percona-live-call-for-hall-of-shame-talks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ve got some spare time on Percona Live during the lightning talks session, and are spontaneously calling for &#34;Hall of Shame&#34; submissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What is this about?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We just had a wonderful &lt;a href=&#34;http://summit2014.reversim.com/agenda&#34;&gt;Reversim Summit&lt;/a&gt; a couple weeks back, where we held the &#34;Hall of Shame&#34; session. We are used to hear talks about success stories and great new technologies. Well, this session is your chance to come up and say: &#34;I messed up, and I&#39;m proud of it!&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will have 3-4 minutes to tell us about how you once accidentally dropped your database; corrupted your data; brought your company&#39;s service down. The greater the damage, the greater the appeal! But we&#39;re looking for the funny edge - not for a tragedy. There are no slides. Just a &#34;Hall of Shame&#34; screen behind you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The response we got on &lt;em&gt;Reversim Summit&lt;/em&gt;? It was amazing. The audience was literally in tears; there were such hilarious stories that we could hardly keep up. People were spontaneously offering their stories and the organizers had to hold them back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be telling about your mess up - so please make sure you feel OK about this. For what it&#39;s worth, I will contribute my own shameful, shameful story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this is new &amp;amp; experimental for the Percona Live conference, and we don&#39;t have many slots. If no one submits - that&#39;s OK. If too many submit, we&#39;ll have to cut most. As conferences go, we may end up with a last moment open timeslot, so if you&#39;re spontaneous that could be your chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Ready to submit?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please send an email to &lt;a&gt;mysql.hall&lt;wbr&gt;&lt;/wbr&gt;ofshame&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;@&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;gmail.com&lt;wbr&gt;&lt;/wbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with a brief description of what you want to share. I&#39;ll be reviewing these submissions and either approve, reject or hold you on a waiting list. I assume this will go by First Come First Served. The deadline for submissions is &lt;strong&gt;Friday, Mar 14th&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percona Live 2014 schedule released; BoF and Lightning Talks Call for Papers continues</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/01/16/percona-live-2014-schedule-released-bof-and-lightning-talks-call-for-papers-continues/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 11:01:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/01/16/percona-live-2014-schedule-released-bof-and-lightning-talks-call-for-papers-continues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The complete tutorial &amp;amp; session schedule for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/&#34;&gt;Percona Live MySQL Conference &amp;amp; Expo 2014&lt;/a&gt; is released. This schedule offers both a sense of achievement as well as a sense of regret; for I believe the schedule is very good, and yet some good proposals had to be left out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an inevitable result of a conference that is popular and receives far more proposals than can fit within the time frames. This conference offers &lt;strong&gt;96&lt;/strong&gt; session slots and &lt;strong&gt;16&lt;/strong&gt; 3-hour tutorial slots. We got well over &lt;strong&gt;300&lt;/strong&gt; proposals -- I&#39;m not even sure how to count them -- and they just can&#39;t all fit in. My sincere apologies to all those left out. A proposal of mine was just rejected yesterday from another conference; I can sympathize and empathize with all turned down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of our interest in having a diversity of talks and speakers, we have promoted talks by less frequent speakers and newly presenting companies. We are happy to grow the community!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although titled &#34;Percona Live&#34;, this conference&#39;s program is managed by a diverse and independent committee. We had good discussions and some very good thinking and advice were offered. I&#39;m happy to acknowledge and thank the committee members:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cédric Peintre, Dailymotion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giuseppe Maxia, Continuent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ivan Zoratti, SkySQL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jay Janssen, Percona&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jeremy Cole, Google&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laine Campbell, PalominoDB (now Blackbird, congrats!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liz van Dijk, Percona&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roland Bouman, Pentaho&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tim Callaghan, Tokutek&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Todd Farmer, Oracle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;myself, Outbrain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the schedule I&#39;m as always eager to attend many more sessions than I can; until I get more replicas of myself, It&#39;s again down to choosing between multiple prominent talks at each time slot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to all those who submitted a proposal! (It&#39;s cool, just saying)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Birds of a Feather, Lightning Talks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Call for papers continues! You are encouraged to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2014/user&#34;&gt;submit your proposals&lt;/a&gt; until end of January. These proposals are reviewed by the committee, and eventually chosen and scheduled by Giuseppe Maxia. See also:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://datacharmer.blogspot.co.il/2013/11/call-for-papers-with-lightning-talks.html&#34;&gt;Call for papers (with lightning talks): Percona Live MySQL Conference 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://datacharmer.blogspot.co.il/2013/12/submissions-at-percona-live-santa-clara.html&#34;&gt;Submissions at Percona Live Santa Clara 2014 and Lightning talks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>common_schema: speaking at Percona Live London, Nov. 2013</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/11/04/common_schema-speaking-at-percona-live-london-nov-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 17:30:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/11/04/common_schema-speaking-at-percona-live-london-nov-2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In one week&#39;s time I&#39;ll be presenting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/london-2013/sessions/commonschema-dbas-framework-mysql&#34;&gt;common_schema: DBA&#39;s framework for MySQL&lt;/a&gt; at Percona Live, London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk introduces the rich toolset known as &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.google.com/p/common-schema/&#34;&gt;common_schema&lt;/a&gt;. It is free, open source, extremely useful in solving DBA &amp;amp; developer tasks, and is the next best thing ever invented next to SQL pie charts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll introduce:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Views, with which you can detect and terminate idle transactions, blocking transactions; roll your range partitions; find duplicate keys; block/unblock accounts; get fine grained privileges per account; find AUTO_ICNREMENT free space; ...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Routines: do meta executions such as eval(); get query checksums; duplicating accounts; killing suspicious connections; security auditing; parsing JSON data; ...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QueryScript: if you&#39;re not using it, you&#39;re missing on a powerful scripting language tightly integrated with SQL/MySQL. We&#39;ll see the basic constructs, variables, loops; the more sophisticated MySQL/locks/overhead/danger aware constructs such as foreach &amp;amp; split; throttling, exceptions, it&#39;s all in there. I&#39;ll present real scripts that saved the day and challenge you to implement them in another scripting language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Briefly introducing rdebug: stored routine debugger and debugging API&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roadmap (some cool things coming along)&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What this talk isn&#39;t&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A tedious &#34;read the manual aloud&#34;. Nor is it a comprehensive listing of all functionality. These would be the surest way of sending you to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What this talk is&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A view into the concepts behind &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt;; the reasons this project has justification to exist; the various problems it solves; and yes, interesting examples. Every single &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; feature was developed out of real world need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am confident you&#39;ll find &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; to have something you need that will improve your work as a developer or a DBA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk is similar to &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/mysql/speaking-at-percona-live-2013-common_schema-lightning-talks&#34;&gt;the one I gave&lt;/a&gt; at Santa Clara this April. It is updated with new content following recent developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/shlominoach/commonschema-22&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>common_schema &amp; openark-kit in the media: #DBHangOps, OurSQL</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/06/26/common_schema-openark-kit-in-the-media-dbhangops-oursql/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2013 21:46:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/06/26/common_schema-openark-kit-in-the-media-dbhangops-oursql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4&gt;#DBHangOps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of joining into &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DBHangops&#34;&gt;@DBHangOps&lt;/a&gt; today, and speak about &lt;a href=&#34;https://code.google.com/p/common-schema/&#34;&gt;common_schema&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.google.com/p/openarkkit/&#34;&gt;openark-kit&lt;/a&gt;. What was meant to be a 15 minute session turned to be 50 -- sorry, people, I don&#39;t talk as much at home, but when it comes to my pet projects...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also realized I was missing on a great event: DBHangOps is a hangout where you can chat and discuss MySQL &amp;amp; related technologies with friends and colleagues, with whom you typically only meet at conferences. I will certainly want to attend future events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to John Cesario and Geoffrey Anderson who invited me to talk, and to the friends and familiar faces who attended; I was happy to talk about my work, and very interested in hearing about how it&#39;s being put to use. We also had time to discuss &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.markleith.co.uk/ps_helper/&#34;&gt;ps_helper&lt;/a&gt; with no other than Mark Leith!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video is &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DBHangops/status/349965939690835970&#34;&gt;available on Twitter/YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;OurSQL&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;openark-kit&lt;/em&gt; has also been &lt;a href=&#34;http://technocation.org/content/oursql-episode-143%3A-biblical-tools&#34;&gt;featured on the OurSQL podcast&lt;/a&gt; by Sheeri &amp;amp; Gerry, who did great coverage of some tools. I will disclose that more is to come; I&#39;m happy this is in capable hands and look further to hear the next episode!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking on the media: OurSQL, Reversim</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/03/21/speaking-on-the-media-oursql-reversim/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 11:51:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/03/21/speaking-on-the-media-oursql-reversim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of speaking on two excellent podcasts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;OurSQL&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No need for me to introduce this podcast. I just have to say it was only when I interviewed that I realized the amount of work taken for producing one single cast. Kudos to Sheeri &amp;amp; Gerry and Rich Goyette the sound producer and thank you for your kind hospitality!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the cast on &lt;a href=&#34;http://technocation.org/content/oursql-episode-129%3A-new-and-extended&#34;&gt;OurSQL Episode 129: New and Extended&lt;/a&gt;, where we speak about the upcoming &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2013/&#34;&gt;Percona Live MySQL Conference &amp;amp; Expo, 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Reversim&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an Israeli, Hebrew speaking podcast, and is undoubtedly the queen of Software Development podcasts here. Run by two enthusiast, veteran, open source keen developers, this is a &lt;em&gt;must hear&lt;/em&gt; podcast if your Hebrew isn&#39;t rusty ;) Thanks Ori &amp;amp; Ran for having me again!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was honored to be interviewed for the 3rd time there, again speaking about MySQL and its ecosystem. In this recent podcast, I speak about the new 5.6 release, highlighting some features; about MariaDB; the Galera cluster technology; LGPL connectors; Percona Live 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the cast on the &lt;em&gt;reversim&lt;/em&gt; website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reversim.com/2013/03/171-mysql-56.html&#34;&gt;171 MySQL 5.6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next speaking event will be at the conference itself; more on that later.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides from my talk: common_schema, DBA&#39;s framework for MySQL</title>
      <link>/blog/2012/12/04/slides-from-my-talk-common_schema-dbas-framework-for-mysql/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Dec 2012 21:51:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2012/12/04/slides-from-my-talk-common_schema-dbas-framework-for-mysql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you&lt;/em&gt; to all who attended &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/london-2012/sessions/commonschema-dbas-framework-mysql&#34;&gt;my talk&lt;/a&gt; at Percona Live London!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slides from my talk are now made available, following: [download id=&#34;2&#34; format=&#34;1&#34;]. Also available on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/shlominoach/slides-commonschema-dbas-framework-for-mysql&#34;&gt;slideshare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They should also be on the Percona Live site within a few days.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking in London: common_schema, DBA&#39;s framework for MySQL</title>
      <link>/blog/2012/11/22/speaking-in-london-common_schema-dbas-framework-for-mysql/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2012 12:35:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2012/11/22/speaking-in-london-common_schema-dbas-framework-for-mysql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m happy to be speaking about &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.google.com/p/common-schema/&#34;&gt;common_schema&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/london-2012/sessions/commonschema-dbas-framework-mysql&#34;&gt;Percona Live London&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Dec 4th, 2012&lt;/strong&gt;. This will be the first chance for me to speak about &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt;, what I believe to be an extremely useful companion to your MySQL server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will show you how &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; can leverage your SQL skills and give you &lt;em&gt;new powers&lt;/em&gt;. Stuff you had to be SQL-Perl-super-expert to work through is easily attainable with &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; and QueryScript. Some maintenance, security and auditing tasks are now a breeze. Writing server side scripts can be fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I &lt;em&gt;won&#39;t&lt;/em&gt; do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the fancy manual aloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk you through every possible view, column, function, parameter and script&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explain the nature of &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt;, show you the concepts behind it (and it is built with concepts in mind)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide with selected examples (schema analysis, security, processes &amp;amp; transactions) -- there&#39;s much to go by, but no boring drill down into all details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expose some cool hacks with &lt;em&gt;QueryScript&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do very brief (as time allows) live demos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt; is an open source project and released under the BSD license.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last April &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2012/sessions/common-schema-framework-mysql-server-administration&#34;&gt;Roland Bouman gave a great talk&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt;. This will not be the same talk; a lot has been developed by this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll be speaking at a very challenging time slot; the three other talks running concurrent to my own are all great ones; I actually wanted to attend all three of them. Heck, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mysqlperformanceblog.com/2012/10/30/percona-live-london-2012-talks-you-do-not-want-to-miss/&#34;&gt;Peter wants to&lt;/a&gt; (though contrary to belief he can&#39;t &lt;em&gt;fork()&lt;/em&gt; himself). So, no hard feelings if you choose another talk during this time slot. But I do know where you live.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>common_schema talk at Percona Live</title>
      <link>/blog/2012/04/08/common_schema-talk-at-percona-live/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Apr 2012 18:57:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2012/04/08/common_schema-talk-at-percona-live/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Are you attending PerconaLive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow me to suggest you attend the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2012/sessions/common-schema-framework-mysql-server-administration&#34;&gt;Common Schema: a framework for MySQL server administration&lt;/a&gt; session on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;April &lt;strong&gt;12&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;14:00 - 14:50&lt;/strong&gt; @ Ballroom F.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk is by none other than &lt;a href=&#34;http://rpbouman.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Roland Bouman&lt;/a&gt;. Roland co-authored parts of &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt;, and is a great speaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a personal interest, of course, being the author of most of the components in &lt;em&gt;common_schema&lt;/em&gt;. I would like to convert you to a supporter of this project. I know a few very smart people who think this project is an important tool. I would like more people to get to know it. Eventually, I would like developers and DBAs alike to consider it an inseparable part of any MySQL installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I shall have world domination, Bwa ha ha!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have fun, I will unfortunately not attend myself this year. Having been on the program committee, I can tell it&#39;s going to be a great conference!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impressions from Percona Live, London</title>
      <link>/blog/2011/10/27/impressions-from-percona-live-london/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2011 19:53:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2011/10/27/impressions-from-percona-live-london/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Am now back from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/london-2011/&#34;&gt;Percona Live&lt;/a&gt;, London. Here are some quick impressions of mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The physical location of the conference was excellent, not far from Tower Bridge. The conference area itself was nice and has good atmosphere. Very well organized. Kudos to &lt;em&gt;Percona&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Theme&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official theme for the conference was &lt;em&gt;&#34;Discover the Power of MySQL&#34;&lt;/em&gt;. However, looking back at the conference, I think the de-facto theme was &lt;em&gt;&#34;High Availability and Scale Out for MySQL&#34;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do I say that? Look at the sponsors of the event; look at the talks. There were talks by and about Clustrix, Tungsten (parallel replication), Schooner, Choosing a HA solution (by Henrik), Fusion-IO, MySQL Cluster, MySQL in the Cloud, Galera Replication, Scalebase, Spider, MHA, Various HA Solutions (by Oli Sennhauser)...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were other talks, about all sorts of things. But to me it seemed like scale-out was the big thing, and HA the next one. Especially looking at sponsors booths it looked that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;People&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, it&#39;s no secret that meeting the people is a great fun. I met with familiar faces, and was happy to meet new ones. It&#39;s great to just discuss stuff with people, share opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The after party was fun, and well organized. Kudos to &lt;em&gt;Clustrix&lt;/em&gt; who sponsored it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Business talk&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn&#39;t at the conference to sell anything myself, and so was on a relaxed mood. I was happy that whatever sales talk I shared, heard or overheard was highly technical and very open. It was also good to openly discuss possible relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was in particular pleased to see the popularity some of my tools and ideas were gaining. I could recognize at least two talks where my tools were mentioned; I was delighted to talk to DBAs telling me they were using &lt;em&gt;openark-kit&lt;/em&gt; in general, &lt;a href=&#34;http://openarkkit.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/openarkkit/doc/html/oak-online-alter-table.html&#34;&gt;oak-online-alter-table&lt;/a&gt; in particular, or some SQL solutions and tricks I offered in my blog. This is really wonderful! To write something having people use it to their benefit -- I suppose this is what open source aspires to. It&#39;s great to hear feedback, and better yet to get good feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also had the pleasure of meeting people after hours, and have good discussions, not necessarily MySQL related.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To top it all, I had free time on Wednesday, where I had a superior visit to the Natural History Museum, which left me in awe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides from my talk: &#34;Programmatic Queries: things you can code with SQL&#34;</title>
      <link>/blog/2011/10/27/slides-from-my-talk-programmatic-queries-things-you-can-code-with-sql/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2011 13:44:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2011/10/27/slides-from-my-talk-programmatic-queries-things-you-can-code-with-sql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are the slides from my talk &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/london-2011/session/programmatic-queries-things-you-can-code-with-sql/&#34;&gt;Programmatic Queries: things you can code with SQL&lt;/a&gt; held on October 25th on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/london-2011/&#34;&gt;Percona Live&lt;/a&gt; event, London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://code.openark.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/programmatic_queries__things_you_can_code_with_sql.pdf&#34;&gt;Programmatic Queries: PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish to thank those who attended my talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The topic of the talk was irregular and, to some extent, controversial. Should one really rely on internal implementation for optimizing her queries? &lt;em&gt;Sergei Golubchik&lt;/em&gt; was quick to suggest that even in current and coming versions of MariaDB, some things I spoke about may not hold true. I accept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was in urge to complete my talk within the time frame. I was happy to hear later on that my talk was well received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were homework to my talk. I thought I would make some contest picking the best answers, stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking on Percona Live, London: &#34;Programmatic Queries: things you can code with SQL&#34;</title>
      <link>/blog/2011/10/10/speaking-on-percona-live-london-programmatic-queries-things-you-can-code-with-sql/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2011 07:48:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2011/10/10/speaking-on-percona-live-london-programmatic-queries-things-you-can-code-with-sql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll be speaking at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/london-2011/&#34;&gt;Percona Live&lt;/a&gt; event, held in London, October &lt;strong&gt;24, 25, 2011&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My session is called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/london-2011/session/programmatic-queries-things-you-can-code-with-sql/&#34;&gt;Programmatic Queries: things you can code with SQL&lt;/a&gt;. It&#39;s a short &lt;strong&gt;30&lt;/strong&gt; minute talk, in which I present underlying knowledge of the programmatic nature of SQL queries within MySQL, and how to take advantage of such knowledge so as to build faster, shorter, and sometimes unexpected queries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; about stored routine programming, a classic programmatic aspect of MySQL, but rather about expected order of execution: of row evaluation, of control flow statements, of table inference, of time issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have far too many examples, some real-world problem solvers, and some less common in daily use, to be able to deliver them all on this session. I will pick up those which seem most interesting to me, or those best presenting the programmatic nature of the query. As time allows I may add more examples, or look into interesting future possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to see you there.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>